<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jaro Says</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+08:00</updated><subtitle>Reflections, Technology, Analytics, and Stories</subtitle><entry><title>Webinar Transcript: What Does a Data Scientist Do in the Working World?</title><link href="/webinar-data-scientist-real-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-01T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-08-01:/webinar-data-scientist-real-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is a raw transcript of my webinar for the students of the Royal Institute School on behalf of the school’s Career Guidance Unit.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is a raw transcript of my webinar for the students of the Royal Institute School on behalf of the school\'s Career Guidance Unit.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone and thank you for that introduction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m aware that the majority of the audience today is O-Level and A-Level students so I’m going to do my very best to keep things simple but informative and hopefully to keep you somewhat entertained as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot that I can talk about on this topic but what I’ll be doing today is, instead of diving deep into one or two specific examples, I’ll give you a few high-level ways of thinking about data science that you can then use to figure out how you can carve out a role for yourself as a professional with data science skills in the business world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to ask questions throughout the webinar, drop them in the chat, and I’ll get to them at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005550.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005550.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this webinar is on the working world, I figured let’s start with why I work in data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent my late teenage years and my early 20s doing a lot of exploration. I worked in market research, I worked in radio, I worked as a voiceover artist, I was an entrepreneur, a digital marketer, a blogger, a salesman, and the whole aim of this mess of affairs and roles, at least in my mind, was to get exposure to as many different problems as possible, so that I could figure out which ones fascinated me enough that I would want to work on it for the rest of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I had some specific criteria for what problems are fascinating to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to wear many different hats or work in many different roles while solving the problem. In other words, I did not want any two days to be the same. I did not want to live a life of monotony where you do the same thing every single day. I wanted the freedom and flexibility to be able to shift into another role that’s different enough to engage me but still relevant to my experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted the problems to require the use of both sides of my brain — the creative right and the analytical left. I knew that the field that would fascinate me would be that which requires using both science and art to solve its problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And finally, and perhaps, most importantly, I wanted to work on problems that are fascinating to everyone, not just to those working in the field. I didn’t want people to turn around and walk away when I start talking to them about what I do. I wanted them to be as fascinated as I am about the amount of potential and possibilities that could be unlocked with solving these problems. Because in all honesty, that’s where the money is. In our digital world, the money is where everyone’s attention is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this led to me stumbling upon data science and data analytics that checked all of this criteria. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005556.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005556.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just so we’re all on the same page because I know there may be students here who don’t exactly know what data science is: very simply put, data science involves extracting insights from raw data, for example patterns and trends, to be used for decision making either by people or by machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you’ve ever bought anything from any major e-commerce store like Amazon or Daraz, you would’ve seen a section titled “customers who were interested in this product, also bought these other products”, so if you were interested in buying a bicycle of a certain premium brand you’d see premium bike seat covers or a high-end bike lock in the recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s happening behind the scenes is that a machine is looking over very large volumes of transaction data, finding patterns in what customers purchase together, and then automatically recommending related products that you might find helpful. And it’s doing this because the company obviously wants you to buy more so they can make as much money from you as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005604.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005604.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s an example of what you can achieve with data science but the really neat thing about data science is that it is so broad it cuts across every single function of an organization and every single industry and appeals to different types of people with different skillsets and different personalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now these are three things I want to expand on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005609.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005609.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the first – cutting across every function and several industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every business in the world is made up of teams of people with certain roles and responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have management (the CEOs, COOs, CFOs, the strategists and planners) who are responsible for steering the ship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have sales and marketing which are responsible for generating business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have finance that’s responsible for ensuring the company stays afloat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have operations or engineering or manufacturing that’s responsible for designing, creating, and delivering products or services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have legal whose job is to ensure the company isn’t breaking any laws or putting itself at risk of being sued.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have HR who needs to make sure there are enough people with the right skills employed by the company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have customer service that needs to help customers with their problems and ensure they’re happy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have IT which needs to make sure all the systems are kept alive and everyone has the tools they need to do their jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could keep going but these are largely the main functions of most organizations and data science is extremely useful and relevant to every single one of these functions. Let me give you some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, management could figure out which regions or markets are the most profitable to expand into because those are really expensive decisions where you can’t afford to make a mistake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, the marketing team can test thousands of different types of advertisements and then spend significantly more on the ones that customers respond to the best thereby maximizing the performance of their campaign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, the finance team can predict if the company is on its way to achieving its revenue and profit targets for the quarter and alert management if it’s not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, the operations team can predict how many orders the company might get in the near future so that they can make sure there are enough people, machines, and warehouse space ready to meet the demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, the legal team can very quickly find past cases similar to whatever legal case they’re facing right now so they spend less time researching and more time strategizing and planning on how to win.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, HR can automatically reduce the 1000s of CVs they’ve gotten for a certain role to just the top 10 that meets all the criteria required for the role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, customer service can proactively reach out to customers who’ve recently bought but are not using their product so they can ensure they don’t regret their purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And using data science, IT can monitor the usage of systems so they can get rid of systems that aren’t in use or shut them down and save some money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this means for data scientists is that you have a buffet of work to choose from. You could be a generalist and work across all these functions or you could be a specialist in, for example marketing analytics or operational analytics, or you could keep jumping around whenever you get bored of one thing. That’s the beauty of data science, there are so many applications within the business world and beyond it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My advice: you’re probably already interested in one of these things, learn it and then pair it with knowledge of data science. Even if you don’t end up being called a data scientist, possessing data science skills along with expertise in a certain domain will put you a notch above the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005615.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005615.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve looked at a range of functions and how data science cuts across all of it. It’s easy to imagine how data science cuts across various industries too. Instead of generic examples across a ton of different industries or the stuff you’ve probably heard about like self-driving cars and highly targeted advertising, I’d like to talk about 3 slightly unorthodox uses of data science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first is farm analytics. This is where data science is used to better manage farms. Think of drones carrying cameras using computer vision to keep track of herds of sheep and cows on a very large farm. Think of sensors being used below and above the land to continuously measure the health of soil and crops and then automatically trigger water and fertilizer dispensers if needed. A lot of this stuff saves farmers a lot of time and labour and it helps them focus on growing more nutritious crops at cheaper prices that eventually benefit all of us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second is sports analytics and I’m going to use Formula 1 as an example. Formula 1 cars have over 300 sensors that generate nearly 1.5 million data points per second. That’s a lot of data and so they need to use high performance computing solutions to crunch all those numbers and put it in formats and visualizations that the engineers and drivers can easily understand. These engineers and drivers then use this information to make changes to the configuration of the car or the drivers use the information to see which parts of the track they need to improve on, for example, on which parts they’re braking too much for or too little for. Because even if they can shave off half a second in their performance, in Formula 1 that can mean the difference between 10th place and 1st place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third is entertainment analytics. There are fascinating case studies about how movie studios are using computer vision to continuously monitor the emotions and engagement of an audience during a test screening of a movie. The program can tell when people are laughing, interested, or just bored based on their facial expressions and body language. So, for example, if the program discovers that nobody laughed after a joke in the movie, the scriptwriters can rewrite that part of the movie and re-test it. That way using data science movie studios can create movies that are highly entertaining from start to finish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is one way of looking at what you could do as a data scientist in the working world. There is another and that takes me back to the other point I wanted to expand on — appealing to different types of people with different skillsets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005624.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005624.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at a typical data science workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We always start with a question we want to answer or a problem we want to solve. For example, which of our customers should we focus on? We have 100,000 but we want to identify the ones that we should spend the most time with and who’ll generate the highest return for our business. Remember companies don’t have infinite resources, there’s only a set amount of money and time you can spend and you need to prioritize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we need to collect data relevant to the question. We need to extract all our customer data from all the systems we’re using in this company and we need to figure out how to put it all together so we’re working with datasets that give us a complete picture of who our customers are and how they’ve interacted with our business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we need to understand and explore this data. Who are our largest customers? Have our biggest customers changed positions over the years? Which data about our customers have issues? How should this data be cleaned?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once we have a good understanding of the data we’re working with and the general patterns and trends, we can begin to think of how we can create a model to predict which customers could potentially generate the most revenue for the company over the next 3 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And then finally, we’ll want to communicate these findings to management and the sales and marketing teams so they can start acting on our findings. We’ll want to create a dashboard for example so everyone can freely explore our findings and dive deeper into the data if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that you could be a data scientist or a data professional that works across the entire workflow and usually in smaller organizations you’re going to have to do that. But in a large organization, you’ll find people specializing in a single aspect of this workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For instance, it’s generally a data-savvy management professional or a strategist that comes up with this question and identifies it as one of the most important things that a company should answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s a data engineer working with systems experts, database administrators, and cloud engineers to figure out how the data should be extracted from systems, transformed, combined, and stored.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s generally a business and data analyst that explores the data, identifies and rectifies its issues and they do this because they have a very good understanding of how the business works and they’re able to tell what’s good and representative data from what’s bad and inaccurate data. A data engineer could help here as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, and most people find this the more interesting part, it’s the machine learning model developers who decide between all the models they know of to figure out which one would get the job done best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And then, it’s the dashboard developers who prepare the reports and dashboards and tell stories to the management and sales and marketing team to convince them that this model is working well and according to its predictions this is who the company should focus on and if they do so, the company could earn 2 times or 3 times more revenue. These dashboard developers could be the business and data analysts as well since who better to tell stories than someone who understands the business deeply. There tends to be some overlap between these roles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And of course, let’s not forget that there will be a data science-savvy project manager overseeing the entire workflow and ensuring the work is getting done according to the set budgets and timelines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there’s a lot of different stuff you can be, how in the world do you decide between all of these roles? This takes me to the final thing I wanted to touch upon, and that is data science appeals to different types of people with different personalities as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005637.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005637.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s simplify your personality and let’s reduce it to two factors. One of those factors is how much you like working with people, the other is how much you like working with technology. There will be some of you, like me, that like working with both — a healthy amount of interactions with customers and management teams as well as interactions with systems and code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that our physical and digital worlds are so tightly integrated, you can’t really choose one and completely avoid the other but you may have a preference or a bias towards one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, wherever you may put yourself in this Venn diagram, there will be a role in data science for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you primarily enjoy working with technology, then you could consider roles like a machine learning engineer or a data engineer. These are really tech heavy roles that require you to, in the case of a machine learning engineer, spend time building models and algorithms and helping the company integrate it into their products or services. In the case of a data engineer, spend time connecting systems, making sense of the organization’s data, and making sure its data is flowing the right way through an organization so it’s available for analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you primarily enjoy working with people and overseeing them and interacting with them and organizing their work, you could consider a role like a data project manager or roles in data product sales which involves establishing a deep understanding of a company’s data product or service and then convincing potential customers to purchase it by telling them how it could solve their specific problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And if you enjoy working with both people and technology, you could consider roles in business and data analytics who are the middlemen between the more technical data resources within a company and the less technical business resources, they’re the translators and the storytellers who help decision makers make data-driven decisions. You can consider roles in business intelligence too and BI specialists don’t just figure out what kinds of dashboards or analytics business leaders need to do their jobs but they also make sure business intelligence tools are configured correctly and the data powering these dashboards is accurate, relevant, and up-to-date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an illustrative example and there may be some of you on the call who’ve got some experience or knowledge and completely disagree and believe that a project manager should sit in the middle or a data analyst should sit on the right or the lines between a data analyst and a BI specialist are really blurry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, different companies do things in different ways and because this is an emerging field the world really hasn’t reached a consensus on where to draw the lines between many of these roles. The key takeaway here is that you can do a lot more with data science skills than just be a guy or girl that builds machine learning models day in and day out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With data science skills you can carve your own path in the business world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005643.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005643.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I stop for questions, I want to leave you with three things that I sincerely believe every aspiring data scientist should learn. This is regardless of your personality type because from experience it’s been incredibly beneficial to my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first is learning to tell stories. We often get lost in the rational and logical aspects of data science because, well, it’s got science in its name. But at the end of the day you want to use insights to convince someone to make a certain decision and what works is not raw facts and figures but emotional stories. This can be in the form of a speech or an interactive visualization or a web application, whatever it is, speak to people’s hearts using data, not their minds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second is learning to embrace mistakes. This is a field that’s growing insanely fast. There is so much I don’t know, there’s so much I need to learn, so naturally I make mistakes. I do the wrong things and I say the wrong things, but you need to be alright with not being perfect. It’s a lifelong learning journey and if you don’t let your mistakes get to you, the journey can be very rewarding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third is learning to empathize. By empathize I mean, putting yourself in the shoes of other people. You don’t necessarily need to be working in an office to do this, you can start by doing it with your friends at school. Whenever they’re facing a problem, try and understand how they feel and why they want that problem solved. If you can do this for your friends, you can do it for your colleagues and your customers and that’ll be very helpful in figuring out how you can use data science to actually enrich people’s lives in the working world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commence Q&amp;amp;A Session&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time today, I hope this was helpful. Feel free to connect with me on LinkedIn, just look for Stefan Jaro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need more information about data science, how you can get started in the field, how RI or RIC can help you, feel free to reach out to the RIC Career Guidance Unit. They’ll set you up for a career of success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again and have a great Friday evening.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>Questions to Reflect on When Considering a Job</title><link href="/questions-considering-job.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-27T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-07-27T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-07-27:/questions-considering-job.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Three questions to reflect on when you\'re considering a new job opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on LinkedIn: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:6957254865915928576/"&gt;Post Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three questions to reflect on when you\'re considering a new job opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will I be solving problems that interest me? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will I be in a supportive environment? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will I be earning enough to be comfortable? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your answer is \"No\" to any of the above, then keep working on yourself until the right opportunity arises because: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the problems don\'t even remotely interest you, you won\'t be able to sustain your enthusiasm after the initial new-job-honeymoon-period is over. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you\'re going to be in a non-supportive environment, you\'ll probably spend more time and effort on irrelevant problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you\'ll be struggling to pay your bills or support your family, you won\'t have the mind-space to focus on the problems you\'ve been assigned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>Well-being in an Economic Crisis: How Business Leaders Should Respond</title><link href="/well-being-economic-crisis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-14T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-07-14T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-07-14:/well-being-economic-crisis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you're a business leader in Sri Lanka right now, then the mental well-being of your employees should be at the top of your list of priorities.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;*Originally posted on LinkedIn: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:6949651126463934464/?updateEntityUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afs_updateV2%3A%28urn%3Ali%3Aactivity%3A6949651126463934464%2CFEED_DETAIL%2CEMPTY%2CDEFAULT%2Cfalse%29"&gt;Post Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're a business leader in Sri Lanka right now, then the mental well-being of your employees should be at the top of your list of priorities.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They're spending 8 hours or more creating a disproportionate amount of value for you, so the least you can do is make sure those 8 hours aren't adding to their growing list of personal problems.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't want them to turn into another brain drain statistic, give them every reason to stick by you through this economic crisis.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means not just having conversations about a resilient mindset but also creating company policies that serve as tangible proof of your commitment to their well-being.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may not be able to change the country's situation, but you can at least change how your business is responding to it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few ideas:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🏠 Allow people to work from home. If they do everything in front of a computer all day, they should not have to worry about getting fuel to get to work.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;💰 If you can't peg their salaries, at least provide some form of inflation relief whenever you can afford it. The gold standard would be a peg + inflation relief since inflation seems to be getting worse.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🫖 Conduct regular one-on-ones where you check up on each person, their workloads, how they're faring, and what kind of support they need. A short, friendly chat goes a really long way.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;😓 Cut the fat from everyone's workloads by de-prioritizing tasks that are non-essential. Encourage your employees to speak up when they feel like they're overwhelmed and are at the risk of burnout.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🧠 Offer professional therapy that's either paid for by the company or is at least subsidized. You may not be equipped to deal with some of the problems your employees now have in their personal lives and that's where a licensed therapist can help.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📚 Offer to pay for continuing education and MOOCs so your employees can continue to upskill themselves and stay competitive. Incentivize their pursuit of knowledge in these times.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🥳 Find any excuse to celebrate something. A new client. A good deliverable. A successful knowledge sharing session. Break the pattern of endless bad news with some joy and respite.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How else can leaders support their employees through this crisis?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>What Makes a World-Class Data Professional?</title><link href="/world-class-data-professional.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-06-10:/world-class-data-professional.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As we got more data projects, and more complex projects at that, we had to evolve from a rag-tag bunch of coders to an established data science and business intelligence unit.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was recently invited to speak at the launch event of the University of London M.Sc. in Data Science at the Royal Institute of Colombo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead of a generic speech on data science and it being the need of the hour at most companies, the Academic Coordinator encouraged me to touch on the more human-side of working in data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is a raw transcript of my speech at the launch of the University of London’s M.Sc. in Data Science at the Royal Institute of Colombo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past four years, I’ve been in a very unique position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had surrounded myself with some of the brightest minds in problem-solving and Stax, the management consultancy I was at, was transitioning from primarily supporting our foreign consultants to becoming a center of excellence in technology and data analytics. This coincided really well with the growth in interest in data in Sri Lanka and among our American clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we got more data projects, and more complex projects at that, we had to evolve from a rag-tag bunch of coders to an established data science and business intelligence unit. Naturally with this came a lot of pressure to up-skill ourselves and we soon found out that there was a particular set of attributes required to be considered a world-class data professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say data professional and not data scientist because this is relevant for data analysts and data engineers as well. Most companies still haven’t drawn very clear boundaries between these three positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Often Forgotten Ingredient&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s get the obvious out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010540.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010540.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every data professional needs to have good statistical intuition. There’s no way around it. Statistics is the foundation of the entire field and at the very least you need to know your descriptive and inferential statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, every data professional needs to know how to use their tools and how to use it well. I’m talking about programming languages, development environments, visualization and dashboarding tools, and so on. This is a technical job so it’s a given that you need to be able to tap into the power of your computer and quite possibly a distributed network of computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on my experience of having worked with data professionals in Sri Lanka and amongst my clients offices, too many data professionals think that this is it. “This is all I need to succeed in business. I know my stats, I know my Python and now I’m ready for the big bucks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue with thinking that data science is the end and not a means to an end is that it can lead to scenarios where companies thump their chests and boast about the cutting edge models or technologies that they’ve implemented in the workplace. But when you look beneath the hood you realize that they’ve had little to no impact on their customers or operations, because they haven’t solved a business problem with financial implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the missing ingredient here? What makes a world-class data professional?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is extremely simple but also very powerful: empathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010545.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010545.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we’re asking our sales people to have empathy, if we’re asking our customer service representatives to have empathy, if we’re asking our leaders to have empathy, then we should demand the same from our data professionals. They may not be on the front-lines unlike the other three, but aren’t these the people tasked with understanding, and making predictions about, our customers, markets, operations, and employees?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy is a powerful trait that influences every other desirable characteristic of a data professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Empathy and Problem Solving&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010552.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010552.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data professionals need to be great problem solvers because they’re in the &lt;em&gt;business of problem solving&lt;/em&gt; wherever they may work. What better way to solve a problem than by being empathetic? What better way to solve a problem than by putting yourself in the shoes of those you’re solving it for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a junior data analyst and somebody asked me to make a report or dig into the data to understand why something was happening, I thought to myself here’s the chance to show off everything I know. I’d make a big report with as many charts, graphs, statistics, and cuts of the data as I could generate and I’d present it to them proudly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I learned the hard way was that this was the worst possible thing you could do to a time-crunched executive. Give them way too many things to look at and make it very difficult for them to make a decision. What I realized was that I was lacking empathy by not respecting their time and their intentions. By wanting to show off what I knew, I wasn’t helping them achieve their objective which was to make a data-driven decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Empathy and Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010557.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010557.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy even influences the technology (or tech stack) chosen to solve a data problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning unlocks a lot of power and it has a wide number of applications. But with that being said, it’s not always the most optimal solution &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes it’s a very simple algorithm that can be easily explained, or sometimes it’s an Excel model that the client can play around with and validate as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, a solution should be based on a client’s level of comfort and preferences because this is the person (or the group of people) who will buy into the solution. The worst thing you can do is build something fancy and expensive that nobody uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World-class data professionals know this. They know that the utility of a solution is far more important than its composition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During our early days as a data science unit, we’d often deal with skeptical clients. People who hadn’t bought into the data-driven decision making movement yet. We discovered that the easiest way for us to convince them was to start with a simple and explainable solution that immediately delivered value and won their trust. We were then able to leverage that trust and familiarity to propose more complex and more sustainable solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Empathy and Communication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can’t be a data professional if you can’t effectively communicate and empathy is what makes world-class data professionals, world-class storytellers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They don’t parrot a list of facts, figures, findings, and trends because they know that logic and reason alone don’t influence decisions and actions. Emotions influence decisions and actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I really like to do with any big data finding is look for the supporting small data stories or anecdotes to back up an overarching trend. I like to look for stories about people and their experiences, stories that an audience can relate to, so that they personally resonate with the analysis and that makes it much easier to drive my points home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World-class data professionals also speak in the language of their audience. They don’t use terms like “gradient descent” or “resilient distributed datasets” if their audience is largely non-technical. Instead, they paint words with pictures and pictures with their words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Empathy and Resilience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010604.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010604.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any data job is a tough job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes our clients don’t know exactly what problem they want to solve. Sometimes you have a dataset that’s extremely messy and you need to have conversations with multiple stakeholders to make sense of it. Sometimes you don’t know how to get something done because you’ve never solved this kind of problem before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is, working in data requires a lot of grit and resilience. You’re frequently going to be lost and confused and you’re frequently going to be making mistakes. A world-class data professional understands that being uncomfortable is the way of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when you have empathy, it makes things easier. When you have empathy, you know why you’re solving a problem. You know who you’re solving it for and you know how their lives will be made easier by your solution. When you understand your purpose and the impact you can have, this big picture perspective will make it far easier for you to be resilient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The management theorist, Simon Sinek, says that if you ask a bricklayer without perspective what he’s doing he’ll tell you he’s building a wall, but if you ask a bricklayer with perspective what he’s doing, he’ll tell you he’s building a home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Closing Statements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of homes, this university was once my home for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s really great that the University of London now has a Masters in Data Science because if it’s anything like my experience of studying Economics, it’ll require students to not just be able to learn complex concepts but to challenge themselves to apply it to a variety of different problems. It’ll require them to learn as much from their colleagues and classmates as they will from their lecturers. It’ll force them to think from multiple perspectives, including the examiner’s perspective, if they want to excel. And in doing so, it’ll build empathy so they can be better and more resilient problem solvers, technologists, and storytellers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I look forward to a new generation of world-class data scientists from RIC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning from the Terra Luna Fiasco</title><link href="/learning-from-terra-luna.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-17T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-05-17T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-05-17:/learning-from-terra-luna.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;More than anything, this fiasco has reminded me that when we stray from logic and embrace emotions during decision making, we can get very badly burned.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Where were you during the great Terra Crash of 2022? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="terra-crash-chart.png" src="/images/terra-crash-chart.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was just a bystander watching the catastrophe unfold on Twitter. The Crypto community went through every stage of grief.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This can't be happening! We demand our money back, no matter the cost! Is there anything we can do to stop this? I can't believe I've lost my life's savings. I have to move on from this.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than anything, this fiasco has reminded me that when we stray from logic and embrace emotions during decision making, we can get very badly burned. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this piece, I'll be outlining the 5 lessons I learned about investing in Crypto as I scoured through hundreds of Tweets during the crisis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't dive into how or why it happened since it's been widely documented and there's still some doubt behind there being an "attacker". You can check out &lt;a href="https://www.coindesk.com/layer2/2022/05/11/the-luna-and-ust-crash-explained-in-5-charts/"&gt;CoinDesk's Analysis on the crash&lt;/a&gt; for more information or watch &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LVanuXZedbs&amp;amp;feature=emb_title"&gt;CoffeeZilla's breakdown&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 1 - Don't invest more than you can afford to lose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common sense: don't invest your rent payments, your life's savings, or money you've borrowed from someone else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can earn more if you invest more, but &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;IT'S NOT WORTH IT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; if the downside risk means not just losing your money but also your livelihood, relationships, and peace of mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These screenshots below were taken from Twitter. I've removed the display names and usernames to protect each person\'s privacy.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-e1652808988485.png" src="/images/image-e1652808988485.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-1-e1652809007472.png" src="/images/image-1-e1652809007472.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-2-e1652809025684.png" src="/images/image-2-e1652809025684.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-3.png" src="/images/image-3.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 2 - If it's too good to be true, it probably is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anchor Protocol promised returns of \~20% for depositing UST. This is incredibly high compared to traditional finance (or TradFi). Moreover, borrowing rates were much lower. Approximately 10% according to one &lt;a href="https://www.fool.com/the-ascent/cryptocurrency/articles/heres-why-im-passing-on-anchors-20-apy/"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this begs the question: how is this system sustainable? If they're not earning enough from borrowings to repay their depositors (and assuming they can't meet the shortfall from staked collateral alone), how are they guaranteeing their advertised returns? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still wrapping my head around a lot of Crypto technobabble, but according to what I've read this was not meant to be a long-term offering. It was a customer acquisition play and their debt obligations were met through a combination of using their reserves and relying on the speculative value of LUNA. They were propping Anchor up artificially. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a short-term "too good to be true" offering that unfortunately unravelled before it could evolve. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-4.png" src="/images/image-4.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ercwl/status/1524836855530893314"&gt;whole thread above&lt;/a&gt; is worth a read. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 3 - Don't put your faith in arrogant founders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven\'t been following Terra for long so I have no idea if Do Kwon (its founder) was arrogant from the get-go or whether he became arrogant over time as his projects did well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He became known for &lt;a href="https://markets.businessinsider.com/news/currencies/terra-usd-ust-luna-do-kwon-poor-critics-crypto-crash-2022-5"&gt;calling his critics "poor"&lt;/a&gt;. He said there'd be &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EncryptedPedro/status/1524531474237640706"&gt;entertainment in watching 95% of Crypto companies fail.&lt;/a&gt;He had earned his "FU Money" and was clearly letting people know. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that being cheeky and snarky are what people love on Twitter, but he seemed to have been blinded by his arrogance and overconfidence. He was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stablekwon/status/1464897977793728514"&gt;warned about a potential vulnerability&lt;/a&gt; but instead of addressing concerns, he challenged billionaires to disrupt his project using a method that would reward them handsomely if it worked. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That seems like a breach of fiduciary duty to me, regardless of whether or not it was the same method used to start the death spiral of UST and LUNA. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-5.png" src="/images/image-5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 4 - Invest based on logic and facts, not emotion and belief&lt;/strong&gt;s&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"We believe in &lt;em&gt;\$SOMECOIN&lt;/em&gt;" is not a reason to buy. "Stay strong" is not a reason to hold. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-6.png" src="/images/image-6.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to get swept up in the emotions of a community. Especially one that's as loud and boisterous as the Crypto community. But if the only reason you're investing is that several anonymous people on a Discord server told you that &lt;em&gt;\$SOMECOIN&lt;/em&gt; is the next biggest thing, you're basically lifting your legs as they place the rug under your feet. Or you're unwittingly taking part in their pump-and-dump scheme where you'll most likely lose out on your investment before you can dump. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DYOR or Do Your Own Research always. If there's not enough information online, be skeptical. If you don't understand their Cryptobabble, be skeptical. If the founders are anonymous or haven't disclosed their experience and credentials, be skeptical. If their community seems like a cult, be skeptical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it's too good to be true, remember Lesson 2. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-8.png" src="/images/image-8.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 5 - The Crypto community still has a lot to figure out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrencies and Blockchain are still emerging technologies, with (in my opinion) a lot of unanswered questions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are algorithmic stablecoins actually feasible? Are fiat-backed stablecoins truly resistant to similar attacks? How do we measure the fair market price of a coin? Is there a point to technical analysis if so much is based on "hype" and emotions? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of work that needs to be done and undoubtedly, a lot more risks the community will need to take. But until we're at a point where we've figured things out, remember that this is a largely unregulated space. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're on a boat, the seas are rough, and you don\'t have a life jacket. Make your decisions accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technology"></category></entry><entry><title>48 Lessons in 48 Months (eBook)</title><link href="/48-lessons-in-48-months.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-13T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-05-13T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-05-13:/48-lessons-in-48-months.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of the term, here are the 48 lessons I\'ve learned from my leaders, colleagues, and clients over the 48 months I spent at Stax, a global strategy consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first term I ever learned in consulting was \"Key Learnings\". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its definition is self-explanatory. Its purpose, however, is powerful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never move on from anything --- a project, an analysis, a report, a conversation --- without spending some time reflecting on what you\'ve learned. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, knowledge, like interest, compounds over time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of the term, here are the 48 lessons I\'ve learned from my leaders, colleagues, and clients over the 48 months I spent at Stax, a global strategy consulting firm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1wO8hgJXfC9nni5M9hMiCMPMABUi2IGd3/view?usp=sharing"&gt;Download the Book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of it is common sense really, but it\'s funny how you tend to forget the little things in the heat of a tough moment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>Our Worship Has Come Full Circle</title><link href="/worship-full-circle.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-06T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-05-06:/worship-full-circle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If the forests were lit ablaze during a thunderstorm, it's because we had angered the thunder gods.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In ancient times, objects, events, and beings guided our worship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient Objects&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were ancestral carvings made of clay, stone or wood. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were gigantic trees, mountains, and boulders whose presence and sight struck us in awe. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were natural, seemingly otherworldly formations -- such as gems and crystals -- discovered in the earth or its cavities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worshipped these objects for they had some unexplainable effect on us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient Events&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the forests were lit ablaze during a thunderstorm, it's because we had angered the thunder gods.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an earthquake destroyed our village, it was a punishment inflicted by the gods of the land.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If rain did not fall and we could not quench our thirst, the water gods were testing our faith. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We felt powerless in the midst of these events, so we cried out to those that determined them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient Beings&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the village shaman's concoctions cured our ailing children, she was gifted our most treasured possessions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the local soothsayer, by an absolute stroke of luck, predicted an eclipse, he was determined to be a supernatural being. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a tribal leader was victorious in conquest over and over again, he was branded a god of war, and a king of kings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beings that successfully challenged the odds, for better or worse, were made worthy of our worship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then came the beliefs in the unseen, the untouched, and the unexperienced. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The religions. The faiths. The philosophies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These beliefs were compelling. They delighted those of us who believed in one and angered those of us that believed in another. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wars were waged. Lives were lost. Voices were silenced and stories forgotten.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, only some beliefs remained. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;History repeats itself.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we call ourselves believers of some faith, we spend most of our time, again guiding our worship through objects, events, and beings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Objects&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are mansions that sit atop hills overlooking affluent neighbourhoods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are sleek vehicles with curves that rival a voluptuous female form. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are mineral-infused devices that we carry in our pockets and call our second brain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worship these objects for they have some unexplainable effect on us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Events&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the economy crashes and millions lose their jobs, it\'s because the very foundations of our systems were shaken too hard. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the military rises in revolution and ousts our democratically appointed leaders, it\'s a message violently sent by an imperialist collective. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If famine breaks out in one country despite the abundance of food in another, it\'s a result of wilful ignorance and wilful inaction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We feel powerless in the midst of these events, so we cry out to those that determine them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Beings&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a business leader creates an offering to service a need we never knew we had, she is handed millions of our dollars. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When charismatic but incapable individuals arise to challenge qualified incumbents who cannot speak to the hearts of the people, they are awarded the highest positions of power. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an individual offers people a spiritual or emotional respite from the monotony of the unending rat race, she is branded a philosopher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beings that successfully challenged the odds, for better or worse, were made worthy of our worship.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>Don’t Wear a Sweater to Bible Rock!</title><link href="/dont-wear-sweater-bible-rock.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-25T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-09-25T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-09-25:/dont-wear-sweater-bible-rock.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On the 16th of January 2016 a couple of friends and I who were on holiday in Kandy began our journey to the summit of Bible Rock or 'Bathelagala' as it's known locally.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preamble:&lt;/strong&gt; I wrote this article in 2016 for a now defunct travel blog called isrilanka.lk. It had a lot of great pictures that my friends contributed but unfortunately I couldn\'t find them, so I dug up whatever I could from Facebook and an archived version of the website and&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;popped them in here.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Also, I\'d like to apologize in advance for my overly-sarcastic tone of voice at the time.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously it's only like 800 meters above sea level. A sweater is the last thing you need. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Flat Out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the 16th of January 2016 a couple of friends and I who were on holiday in Kandy began our journey to the summit of Bible Rock or 'Bathelagala' as it's known locally. Eh, 'summit' may be overdramatizing it a bit since it isn't a difficult climb. On a scale of Kirigalpoththa to Alagalla, I'd rank it's difficulty a little below Sigiriya (please don't take my rankings seriously, I haven't climbed Kirigalpoththa nor Alagalla, but I promise to revise this once I do). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've ever been unlucky enough to have your phone battery die on any journey from Colombo to Kandy (or vice versa), and had to sadly resort to staring out the window to admire the scenery (something absolutely alien to you goldfish-minded people), you'd have probably seen Bible Rock. It's impossible to miss. It's a completely flat rock quite similar to, and often mistaken for Sigiriya. Well maybe 'completely-flat' is pushing it a little. Think of it as an opposite-Kim-Kardashian - almost flat with a few bumps here and there (this is a very complex joke; I don't expect you to get it). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we stocked up on plenty of water, snacks, first aid, a change of clothes, and desperate pleas (to our respective supreme beings) for greater endurance, before heading out to the Kandy public bus depot. We took a bus heading to Mawanella and from the Mawanella bus depot another bus heading to Aranayake before getting off at the main junction in Gewilipitiya (which is somewhat at the halfway point between Mawanella and Aranayake).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We quickly gobbled down some hot breakfast (mmm...Gewilipitiya &lt;em&gt;parata&lt;/em&gt;), emptied our bladders in the bathrooms of some kind &lt;em&gt;Mudalali's&lt;/em&gt; reception hall, and then grabbed a tuk to the starting point of the climb. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bible-rock-from-afar-1024x574.jpg" src="/images/bible-rock-from-afar-1024x574.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now here's the thing - there are two starting points for the climb. One is where the road to the beginning of the trail begins (which should cost you about 100 rupees to get there from the Gewilipitiya junction), and the other is 1.5 to 2 kilometers up this road to the start of the natural trail (which would cost you about 400 to 600 rupees from the junction since the tuk drivers will argue that they have to climb a steep hill to get there).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course where you decide to start depends on how much time you have (as 2 kilometers up a hill on a road with many bends will take some time) and on whether you'd like to proudly proclaim that you began from the 'true starting point' and not the starting point of the weak and feeble. Also please note that since the tuks aren't metered, how much you end up paying them is entirely dependent on your negotiation skills, the colour of your skin, and the clothes you're wearing (seriously dude, it's a hike, not a mountain catwalk. Lay off the fancy stuff!). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Steps, Steps, Stone Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trail up the mountain is an ascent from the very beginning and gets steeper and steeper as you continue onward. It's very shrub-y at first, then becomes jungle-y and then becomes extremely rocky. The shrub-y and jungle-y parts are a bit of a breeze especially if you're lucky enough to climb on a fairly hot day and not have to endure your friends screaming every five minutes at leeches so tiny you'd mistake them for Donald Trump's junk (but seriously those bastards are like slack-jawed desperados at Hikka beach parties impatiently waiting to pounce on the first unescorted girl they see).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bible-rock-steps.jpg" src="/images/bible-rock-steps.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the jungle-y bit does have stone steps but you've always got to watch your step cause some of those steps can be pretty darn steep steps (this is rhyming on a Pitbull level). The initial steep bits do have a metal, thick, wire-like railing to cling on to but we discovered that in the most steepest of areas - where there's more rock than step - the damn railing had loosened or was just broken and unhelpful.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless the inconvenience was thrilling because a slight form of danger is always going to make up the best types of adventures (and honestly if you're looking for convenience on your adventures just stick to the damn escalator at Majestic City). Even if you do fall, you won't tumble to your death, you'd more likely just violently crash and stop against a tree, and we all know trees are soft and welcome things (I'm just joking, it's not that dangerous...or am I? I guess you'll have to see for yourself). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we reached the rocky bit of the ascent we had to slow down and be a lot more careful. There were waist-high rocks we had to climb up, loose stones that were clearly naturally placed there for a big fat laugh, and at one point a very narrow rock edge that had to be crossed like you're walking on training-tightrope (it's a not-so-steep drop on one side but it's definitely an '&lt;em&gt;ouchie&lt;/em&gt;' drop). Once you've gotten past that there's another bit of shrub-iness and you can pat yourself on the back, raise your arms high, and pretend you\'re Rocky in that scene he celebrates after running up the stairs (don't forget the music!).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did, however, discover another way of getting to the top after the jungle-y bit. If you're feeling adventurous enough (and if you've got great medical coverage), you can use the thick metal wire hanging off a relatively steep slope to pull yourself up to the top of the mountain (my my check out the upper body strength on you, you cheeky gym rat). Do beware though that while literally anyone can come up the way we did, the tug-of-war-with-a-mountain method is best reserved for those brimming with fitness, confidence and as usual, a slight amount of 'nothing is going to go wrong machang!' &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Suicidal View&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When do you get to the top you'll see a little clearing (where someone had clearly camped the previous night) and two paths on either side leading through very tall grass. We took the first path leading to the right and came to a stop at a very old and thoroughly scribbled on (V loves D amiright?) shelter. I looked down the side of a small cliff nearby and I saw...well...I'll be honest with you, I saw a pair of whitey-tighties and a pink pair of panties that had clearly been hurriedly tossed aside in the deranged fury of love-making. Not wanting to disturb anyone (who knows? Maybe it was a budget honeymoon or a married couple desperately trying to rekindle the romantic flame) we quickly gobbled down a few biscuits and headed back to the clearing and through the other path (to get to the other side of the mountain make sure to continue beyond the end of the path by climbing over the rocks). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the skies only slightly cloudy and the warm sun lighting up the land, the view from the edge of the mountain was absolutely heavenly. We were on the side overlooking dense forests spread over mountain ranges and large clumps of trees that extended endlessly towards the horizon. With only a few tiny towns scattered through the landscape, and the clouds leaving large shadows on the land, the view nothing but natural magnificence. It was downright every bit worth the enduring 45-minute climb.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bible-rock-view.jpg" src="/images/bible-rock-view.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact all I wanted to do was drop everything in my life, build with my bare hands a house on one of the mountain tops (if Ryan Gosling can do it in The Notebook so can I), and live the rest of my days as a starved scavenger eating up the view around him as daily nutrition. I stood by the edge and for a brief moment I considered jumping off because who the hell wants to die with a concrete jungle or a hospital room being the last scene they ever see (this is a dark joke, if you know me don't worry about me, I'm not suicidal).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My serene thoughts were then rudely disturbed by how absolutely hot it was getting! Why the hell did I keep wearing my sweater!? Curse the friend who told me it would be slightly cold up there! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bible-rock-view-2-1024x296.jpg" src="/images/bible-rock-view-2-1024x296.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Descending Tea Party&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few photoshoots we began our sad descent down. We decided to walk down the road we previously tuk-ed, back to the main road (despite how tired some of us were because all of us actively live the thug life). We stopped for a short break by a little wooden shop whose old shopkeeper sold us tasty plain tea and tiny bananas (the shopkeeper's friend who was equally old was totally smoking some dank ganja by the way).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acting upon the old man's advice we took a detour down a more natural path (which was 'supposedly' a shortcut) and ended up right as the bus stand near the Hathgampala Maha Vidyalaya. We then collectively chugged down tons of water and ignored the many quizzical stares at our sweaters (seriously why the hell were we still wearing them!?) on our bus ride back to the Kandy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What an adventure! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can stop reading now and get back to your miserable life behind your desk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS&lt;/strong&gt;: If you're going to climb Bible Rock, don't be an asshole and pollute the environment like the assholes that climbed before us. If you bring the trash up the mountain, please be kind enough to take the trash down the mountain. No one's going to do it for you (if you think the municipal council is going to clean this, you must be off your damn mind, it sometimes takes weeks for my garbage to be collected and I don't live on a remote rock).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Stories"></category></entry><entry><title>The Best of Budget Sinobuds: A Deeply Personal Purchase Journey and a Day One Review of the Haylou W1 TWS Earbuds</title><link href="/haylor-w1-day-one-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-09-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-09-18:/haylor-w1-day-one-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been meaning to get a good pair of wireless earbuds for work.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718004750.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718004750.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's this viral video on YouTube of an excited teenage girl receiving a brand new iPhone for Christmas. She squeals in delight when she takes it out of the bag, her eyes radiating a million thank yous. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her hurry to place her hands on a premium assembly of rare minerals and human ingenuity, she opens the box the wrong way and drops the phone on the ground. Cautioning voices behind the camera instantly turn into gasps of frustration. She picks it up, looks at the screen, and bursts into tears. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You watch this and you think, "God! Why can't people be a little more careful with electronics!? Especially brand new ones!? Why don't they understand the value of money? What's wrong with some people!? I know she's just a kid but come on, as a teenager, she's old enough to know better!" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I dropped the charging case of my Haylou W1 TWS Earbuds as I was popping it out of its packaging. Sure, it's no iPhone but it did cost money and it is brand new. Thankfully, it isn't damaged (visibly at least). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesson learned. Don't judge people in viral videos. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello!? Can You Hear Me!?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been meaning to get a good pair of wireless earbuds for work. Like most of you stuck in a pandemic-induced WFH loop, I'm on calls for several hours every single day. It's really frustrating when you're tight on time but you can't hear someone clearly and you need to, again, run through a near-ritualized troubleshooting process: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it my internet? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it their internet?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it my headset?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it their headset?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it my audio configuration?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it their audio configuration?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it Teams/Zoom?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I need to restart my computer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they need to restart their computer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can't we just get on a regular phone call? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I certainly didn't want to be the source of auditory annoyance for anyone else, much less my clients, so I've been using a trusty wired headset with a microphone extension for the longest time. I got it for cheap (less than 10 dollars or 2000 Sri Lankan rupees) but it's been great, people have been able to hear me well, and I'm very rarely the source of an issue. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking the Dystopian Leash&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing about a wired headset though. After a year-and-a-half of working from home, it leaves you feeling like you're putting a leash on yourself each time you get on a call. There's only so far you can travel from your laptop before the jack pops out. And I've learned that I think and speak better when I'm on my feet and I'm pacing about. I've tried walking around with my laptop but after a while it feels like you're on a dystopian dog walk --- the robots are walking you! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some calls like webinars or company announcements where you need to only be listening and I've been wishing I could break away from the screen and wiggle my body around a bit so it doesn't gradually freeze into a permanent sedentary state. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all this in mind I had three primary requirements from a wireless headset: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It needs to be relatively cheap and available in Sri Lanka.&lt;/strong&gt; Like any decent Asian, I'm awfully sensitive to high prices, but like any decent techie, I also understand that you need to spend a bit if you want something good and will last long. This dichotomy was made worse by the fact that our import restrictions have reduced the flow of new electronics to a trickle and this trickle is now ridiculously marked up. With few good choices, this was going to be tough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It needs to have an acceptable microphone with good noise filtration.&lt;/strong&gt; I'm not ashamed to admit that I talk for a living but this means my livelihood depends on the clarity of my voice. I     tested out an old pair of wireless earbuds that I received as a gift a year ago but my ceiling fan made it sound like I was hanging off a helicopter. Noise reduction was a must!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It needs to have satisfactory battery life.&lt;/strong&gt; Last year I purchased a cheap single-ear Bluetooth headset. I wanted to feel like a busy corporate executive (in pyjamas instead of a fancy suit)     that's always on the go (in my home instead of a bustling office). Unfortunately, it had a terrible battery life and had a very bad habit of announcing "Battery Low, Please Recharge" over and over again in my ear during the worst possible moments. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll notice that high-quality audio isn't in the list above. I love music, but I'm not an audiophile and my current pair of earbuds gets the job done for me. Besides, this is meant for calls and I was ready to sacrifice output for input. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn't have to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718004928.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718004928.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earbuds? Sinobuds!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sri Lanka's good relationship with China has translated into almost every online electronic store carrying a wide range of Chinese goods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not complaining. Over the years Chinese electronics manufacturers have really upped their game. Their stuff is pure value for money now. I've been using a Redmi Note 9 Pro for the last 10 months and I haven't had a single thing to complain about. Now I'm not a flagship guy, but compared to the mid-range Samsung, Nokia, and HTC phones I've used, the Redmi has been nothing short of fast, snappy, and sleek. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured I'd choose among the many Chinese earbuds and when I started my search, one brand, in particular, stood out because they've flooded the market with a variety of models: Haylou. They're quite a new company but they've secured funding from Xiaomi who are the manufacturers of my phone, so that earned them a nice, big, green check-mark of approval in my book. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being relatively new to the market, they're certainly not obscure. They've got quite a decent following of product reviewers and quite a number of customer reviews too. When I couldn't decide between the Haylou GT3 Pro, the Haylou GT5, the Haylou Moripods and the Haylou W1, these guys came through for me. To the ones who've added chapters to their YouTube videos that allowed me to immediately skip ahead to the microphone test: thank you, I hope you are blessed with everything you desire in life. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CD32rrF7IXU?start=365" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the information I had, I rolled the dice on the Haylou W1 and bought it for roughly 7,800 Sri Lankan rupees (or 40 USD). I really wanted the blue version but every store I checked selling it for a reasonable price had only the white. I'm not disappointed though, the white still looks pretty neat and overall, I think the price is a steal given the microphone's quality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impressing with Impressive First Impressions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full disclaimer: I've been using the Haylou W1 Total Wireless Earbuds for only a day now, but like all narcissistic product reviewers I believe that to be sufficient enough time to share my detailed observations with you. In fact, I've come up with my own framework for reviewing these earbuds. It's called BATMAN or &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;attery, &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;udio, &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;ouch, &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;icrophone, &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;esthetic, and &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;oise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the &lt;strong&gt;microphone&lt;/strong&gt; since that's one of the primary reasons I bought this. I've been on calls the entire day and everyone's been able to hear me very clearly. Somebody even said that I sounded better through this microphone than the one on my wired headset. Huge win and that's probably down to the 4 microphones this bad boy has in its stems, 2 in each earbud. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part is the &lt;strong&gt;noise&lt;/strong&gt; cancellation. I decided to be a bit of a jerk and generate some noise in the background while speaking to a friend and they weren't able to tell I was being a jerk! This is fantastic! I can now freely dash pots and pans in the middle of frustrating meetings and totally get away with it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005037.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005037.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not a monster, I did listen to a bit of music and one podcast with it (&lt;strong&gt;audio&lt;/strong&gt; in other words). Now I can't comment on highs and lows, or bass and treble, or whether some hips are more truthful than others, but what I can tell you is that it's very decent for its price point. Imagine Dragons sounds good, Kanye sounds good, Doja Cat sounds good, and you can hear the tea-toned specks of saliva flying off British lips during the BBC's World Service (that's an exaggeration but they do sound good). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005053.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005053.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this while I've been draining its &lt;strong&gt;battery&lt;/strong&gt; but it's doing just fine. Some earbuds tend to stutter and lose connectivity when they're low on charge, but I haven't had that problem yet. The website promises 6 hours on a single charge and 20 hours overall with the case. I can only speak non-stop for 4 hours a day so I think I'm good. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;touch&lt;/strong&gt; controls are very simple so they're perfect for my simple mind. If you wanted me to summarize them I'd say: touch to stop, touch to start, touch touch to skip, and touch touch touch to call the nice Google lady on your phone. I was afraid it would be too sensitive and switch off every time I brushed my ear but it turns out I don't brush my ear as much as I thought I did. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005103.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005103.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the &lt;strong&gt;aesthetic.&lt;/strong&gt; There's definitely a little bit of AirPod Pro copycatting going on but there are hints of their own style as well, especially with the stem. They're light and they fit snugly so you can wear them comfortably for hours while blocking out some noise. I recommend wearing them while meditating so you can hear the therapeutic beats of your heart. I'm not crazy about the build of the charging case. The lid seems a little loose (although that could be from when I dropped it), it's shaped like an egg, and it's smooth and plasticky, but this is probably just me being pedantic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I'm impressed. I definitely believe it's worth 40 USD. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Before You Leave, A Message From Our Sponsors&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm kidding, Haylou didn't sponsor this article. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was curious about what Haylou meant. I figured it was something about audio in Chinese. Probably something meaningful. Perhaps renewing or augmenting our basic human auditory capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, I was both right and wrong. Haylou is just how they pronounce "Hello" over there. But that "Hello" can spark a deep appreciation of the human voice...and for some reason, of the ocean through a conch shell. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not kidding, here's what's on their website: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand name is taken from the homonym of the English word "Hello". &amp;gt; We believe that we can resonate with the sea through conch and listen &amp;gt; to the voice of the ocean together, and we can also listen to the &amp;gt; voice of users through Haylou and share the beauty of the voice &amp;gt; together. Haylou is the messenger of sound and the medium through &amp;gt; which we resonate with our users. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever their copywriter was smoking that day, I want some.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technology"></category></entry><entry><title>More Like Beau: Why I’m Looking For Stories in My Daily Life</title><link href="/more-like-beau.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-08-18:/more-like-beau.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, my life started feeling rather ordinary. I woke up, I worked, I exercised, I slept, I repeated. There was no adventure, there was no surprise around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I live on my phone and my laptop more than I live in the world. I think that that's been true for most of us during this pandemic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've been robbed of our opportunity to travel, hike, camp, be intimate, go out for coffee, try new food, make new friends, and form stronger bonds with existing ones. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-3-576x1024.jpeg" src="/images/image-3-576x1024.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure you can do the last one on Zoom but a conversation in person &lt;em&gt;just hits different.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my life started feeling rather ordinary. I woke up, I worked, I exercised, I slept, I repeated. There was no adventure, there was no surprise around the corner, and with these constant (but necessary) lockdowns there was no more looking forward to a night out or a holiday in the countryside. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What'd I do because I couldn't get my adventure fix? I turned to the virtual world. I began inhaling videos and articles about how other people live their lives in a variety of exciting ways. This sea of online personalities with their jaw-dropping feats, interesting jobs, and hilarious quirks was my respite: my break away from the monotony of daily life. For a moment, all I lived to do was experience somebody else's story. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I discovered Beau Miles. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beau isn't your typical Youtuber. He doesn't upload very often. He doesn't have millions of subscribers (although he really ought to). His videos aren't overly-edited barrages of clips with a screaming narrator. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beau is a Professor of Adventure Education at Monash University, Australia. He's got a doctorate in the subject! He lives on a farm with his wife and kid. He collects junk (mostly wood) by the side of the road and uses his carpentry skills to breathe life into them. Oh, and he runs...a lot. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-5 1.png" src="/images/image-5 1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first stumbled upon his channel, I started with his older content. The man has paddled 2000km in a canoe around the southern tip of Africa! Over time, however, his adventures began taking place in and around his neighbourhood. Like the time he ran a mile every hour and spent every minute in-between getting through a lengthy to-do list. Or the time he spent a night on a 100-year old Gum tree right outside his farm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he began to embrace spending time in and around his home, his content began changing my perspective towards my locked-down life. See, Beau wasn't "going" on adventures anymore, he was "finding" them. He would look at something ordinary, like the remnants of an abandoned railroad, and then decide to celebrate its history by running its length dressed as a train conductor holding a coal shovel. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rxCghemtjjM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, 43km isn't really within the radius of a "neighbourhood" but Australia is a massive place so their neighbourhoods are much bigger than ours &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wondered, to make my life more interesting, do I just need to pay more attention to what's around me? Unglue my face from the black mirror and appreciate an environment I have for so long ignored in favour of the thrills of the internet? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of "perception" is the meaning you assign to your sensory input. In other words, it's the internal story that you write in your mind whenever you experience something. The better your perception, the more meaningful your experiences are, and by extension, your stories become more interesting and perhaps, extraordinary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same vein, a human life is simply a collection of stories written every day. When each day's chapter begins to sound the same you feel like chucking the book out the window. But when you start sharpening your perception: spending more time observing and reflecting than drowning out your senses with audio and video, you begin to realize that even the seemingly mundane has something of interest to offer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beau Miles and his wacky adventures didn't lead me to this realization. He planted the seed of course, but the several herniated discs in my spine watered it. After a terrible episode of pain that left me bedridden for a few days, my physiotherapist suggested a daily walk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, the walks were simply a necessity. I turned on a podcast, made my way around my neighbourhood, and resumed whatever I was up to at home. Then, in the spirit of "What Would Beau Do", I started paying more attention to the people and things around me on my walks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-4.jpeg" src="/images/image-4.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started noticing things about my neighbourhood that have somehow escaped me for years. Like the fact that there's a quaint little coffee shop near my house (which I'll visit once COVID eases again) or the fact that between every set of nice properties there are run-down houses. The rich and the poor living side-by-side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A distant neighbour also has two humongous dogs that bark their guts out every time I walk past them. They can't see it through my mask, but I'm pretty sure they can smell my fear. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-5.jpeg" src="/images/image-5.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the most interesting to observe are the people. I don't know many of these people, especially the ones further away from home. I can only imagine what they must be thinking or going through, but often their body language speaks volumes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are the forlorn faces staring out of shop windows, perhaps wondering if their tills will ever weigh heavy again. There are the worried eyes peering above double-masks with long strides and a quick pace, perhaps rushing home to avoid a disease that seems to lurk around every corner. There are the labourers, like the garage mechanic twisting a wrench under a car, fixing it up perhaps for some customer's hopeful wish for a road trip in the near future. And then, on the other end of the spectrum, we have the arrogant, masking nothing but their necks and going about their lives unbothered by the pandemic. Perhaps the statistics haven't turned to names for them yet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My back pain isn't the only reason I walk anymore. It's become a therapeutic experience. I adjust my route around my neighbourhood every once in a while for a change of scenery but the process remains the same. Walk, observe, and look for stories. I'm not looking to spin a long yarn, I'm just in search of little internal realizations that I can add to my life's story so that no two chapters sound the same. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working on my perception has had a tremendous impact on my perspective. When you tell yourself stories of how difficult the lives around you seem to be, you feel grateful for what you have. When you realize you're walking for leisure while others walk for their livelihood, you feel thankful for a job you can do from home. When you actually get out of the house and use your neck muscles and your eyeballs, you realize your neighbourhood has so much more to offer than you thought. And when you add it all up, life won't seem so ordinary after all. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I set off on my walk a little too late in the evening, walked down a dimly lit road and accidentally invaded a dog's personal space. After I finished getting away from him, I got caught in a sudden storm. To add insult to my drenched injury, I was splashed by a car. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'm no Beau Miles, but that's as much adventure as I've had in the past few months and I'll take it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>Lessons In Love and Resilience From My Grandmother</title><link href="/lessons-in-love-resilience-grandmother.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-31T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-07-31T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-07-31:/lessons-in-love-resilience-grandmother.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some people wear these moments of darkness like a cloak, concealed in the thoughts of the past and what could have been. But Neney lit candles in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-1-1024x1024.png" src="/images/image-1-1024x1024.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime during the early part of the year, at the end of a regular weekend visit, I sat down next to my &lt;em&gt;Neney&lt;/em&gt; (grandmother) to say goodbye. She always hated it when we left her, even when we promised we would return the next day or the next weekend. She usually protested with "don't go, stay here with me" or "why do you need to leave", but this time was different. This time, she grabbed my hand and said "stay". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was something in the way she firmly held my hand that moved me. She had been bedridden for some time now and didn't have a lot of energy throughout the day, so this little act was far more taxing for her than it would be for you or me. She didn't say anything. She just closed her eyes and enjoyed a few more moments of being together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-1.jpeg" src="/images/image-1.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My grandmother had a difficult life. She wasn't born into wealth and she dropped out of school after eighth grade. She went hungry to feed her children. She lost her husband far too early. She lost two children, when they were toddlers. She tragically lost another child, more recently and very suddenly. No parent should ever have to bury a child, much less three. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people wear these moments of darkness like a cloak, concealed in the thoughts of the past and what could have been. But Neney lit candles in the dark. From grief, she drew greater love for her family. She expressed her love by turning every interaction, no matter how brief, into an occasion. You couldn't walk away from her without your belly full and without having engaged in a long conversation, often packed with as many questions as an episode of Larry King Live. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our family used to joke about the number of questions she would ask. She was highly inquisitive so she wanted to know everything about you, what you were up to, and how you were feeling. She's probably the reason I have the endurance to get through long exams and job interviews. Looking back, I've come to understand that this was her subtle way of extending your stay, of absorbing your presence, and of making sure you were happy. Having realized the bitter truth of life's impermanence, her job was to make sure you felt loved and she was always on the clock. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-2.png" src="/images/image-2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-3 1.png" src="/images/image-3 1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever we spoke of problems or trouble, she leaned on her philosophy of life, brilliantly summed up in four jovial words --- "what is that so?" Posed as a question, it really made you think about the gravity of your problem and whether you were spending far too much time ruminating over something that just wouldn't matter in the grand scheme of things. This was her wonderful way of switching on your positive thinking. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neney loved creativity in all its forms. She was a voracious reader who would mouth the words silently to herself as she read (I didn't realize I had picked that up from her until I was a teenager). She loved films, music, and social events. She also encouraged us to be creative. She often asked me to give a speech at her birthday, and always demanded a written copy of the speech afterwards. Similarly, after any event, she absolutely needed to get her hands on the photos taken. Her appreciation for creativity made her a collector of family memorabilia and she made sure to revisit them often. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-2.jpeg" src="/images/image-2.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-4 1.png" src="/images/image-4 1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that was really the extent of her demands. Despite giving so much of her time, attention, and energy, she desired very little in return. That's because she never wanted to be a burden. You could see it in her face when she wasn't able to get out of bed more often. She yearned to have more energy, she yearned to be in the center of the crowd, she yearned to be the caretaker. So even though her body started giving way, she never let her mind go. She still wanted to be present, she still wanted to recognize and converse. To give you something in return for the trouble you had taken to come see her. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ezmaline Zunaiha Jaro died during the Holy Month of Ramadan on the 25th of April 2021 at 91 years of age. She was very religious, prayed five times a day, and would've wanted a traditional Muslim burial. Thanks to several members of the family, we were able to give her that, despite the pandemic. God also blessed her, for one last time, in another special way. She had been waiting a year to see her youngest son, and when she passed away, it was in his arms. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neney would've been 92 on the 2nd of August 2021. I know she would want us to celebrate her life and not dwell on our loss. And if she were around and saw any of us being sad for too long, I'd expect she'd give us a big hug and say "what is that so?" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1_5hH6T6Nghg44MAvADZ8tUA.jpg" src="/images/1_5hH6T6Nghg44MAvADZ8tUA.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>Social Media: The Tobacco of My Generation</title><link href="/social-media-tobacco.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-08T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-11-08T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-11-08:/social-media-tobacco.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;That toxic thought spread its tentacles to the other parts of my life too until everything I used to love and enjoy --- reading that fed my brain, conversations that fed my soul, exercise that fed my body --- were laid by the wayside in favour of a blue glow on my face&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;"I think I'm addicted to social media." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This descent to madness was gradual. What started with "&lt;em&gt;How much harm can this do? Let me spend a few more minutes on it&lt;/em&gt;" turned into "&lt;em&gt;I'd rather be on YouTube than hang out with her, she can't possibly be more interesting than all these clips on my 'Watch Later' list&lt;/em&gt;". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That toxic thought spread its tentacles to the other parts of my life too until everything I used to love and enjoy --- reading that fed my brain, conversations that fed my soul, exercise that fed my body --- were laid by the wayside in favour of a blue glow on my face. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worse yet, months of spending hours chewing up whatever Facebook, Instagram, and YouTube wanted me to digest had turned me into an unfocused, demotivated, and easily irritable person. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Experiment on Myself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems ridiculous at first. How do comedy skits, cat videos, memes, and posts from your friends turn you into that kind of person? It was difficult to find a convincing answer at the time because it seemed like social media addiction research was still in its infancy. People were just coming to grips with the damaging effects newsfeeds have on our brain, &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@stefanjaro/the-field-guide-to-spotting-fake-news-in-the-wild-4e747b5031f2"&gt;not just with misinformation&lt;/a&gt; but with prolonged and obsessive use as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718004244.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718004244.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to do two things --- educate myself about what I was doing to my brain with social media and experiment on myself by quitting it, cold turkey, for 6 months and closely observing the resulting behavioural changes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by informing my friends that I wasn't going to be using social media for a while, deleting all of the apps on my phone, and changing their passwords to long obscure ones filled with random characters that I would never be able to remember. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I waited. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitchy Fingers, Twitchy Mind&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I observed was that I didn't know what to do with my hands anymore. I would grab my phone, turn it on, look through my apps, and turn it back off. I'd do this constantly knowing fully well I didn't have any more social apps to go on and that I wasn't allowed to reinstall them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt like I just needed to scroll for some reason. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why every successful social media platform has an endless newsfeed of content? Have you ever wondered why all of them allow you to refresh their newsfeeds by swiping down from the top of your screen? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is engineered for addiction. If you've watched &lt;a href="https://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_social_dilemma"&gt;The Social Dilemma&lt;/a&gt; (and I highly recommend you do) you know this already. It's based on the same design principles as a slot machine at a casino. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like gamblers are addicted to pulling a lever because the next pull might result in a prize, so was I with scrolling through newsfeeds because the next scroll might result in a video, image, or article that I'd find entertaining. When the first twenty or so posts were things I didn't find interesting, I'd scroll back up to the top and pull the lever to refresh it, desperately hoping that something in this new list would give me my much-needed &lt;a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/intl/basics/dopamine"&gt;dopamine&lt;/a&gt; rush. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for the first few weeks after quitting, I felt worse. A lack of constant surges of dopamine worsened my mood. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Thief of Joy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next thing I observed was the occasional urge to see what someone was up to. Somebody's name would pop into my mind and I'd want to see where they were, how they were feeling, and what they had done. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After meditating on these urges I realized that when I used to do this, I would consciously or subconsciously compare myself, my circumstances, and my achievements to theirs. This always, without fail, led to a feeling of inadequacy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I scrolled through the posts of my friends --- their happy moments, their promotions, their wonderful holidays, their master's degrees and everything else --- in my mind, the highlights of their different lives were combined and transformed into a timeline of a single high-achieving individual. In other words, the names on the posts began to blur and it felt like all of these incredible moments had been posted by a single person whom I couldn't dream of measuring up to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inadequacy results in a self-blame game. You punch yourself for every decision you've made that didn't result in a similar life. You completely disregard the fact that these are the &lt;em&gt;highlights&lt;/em&gt; of different people's lives and highlights by nature are rare occasions with large gaps in time between them where nothing but hard work is done. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You treat yourself unfairly. Forgetting the circumstances you were in and what you thought was right at the time. Disregarding all of the hard work that led to your achievements no matter how small. Failing to remember the wonderful holidays you've had and the beautiful moments you've shared with your friends. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to what you might think, these feelings never motivated me to change things because there was always someone out there who had done more and had done better. Constant comparison is the thief of joy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Escaping a Fishbowl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One or two months into the experiment I began to notice that my attention span had grown and my focus had sharpened. I was now able to read for longer and watch lengthy videos without itching to move on to the next thing. Perhaps the best part of this was being able to pay greater attention to people during conversations and not have my mind drift off. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an awful lot of truth behind the joke that people have the attention span of goldfish when they're on social media (&lt;a href="https://time.com/3858309/attention-spans-goldfish/"&gt;ironically goldfish now have longer attention spans than humans&lt;/a&gt;). The problem is that it carries forward to the other areas of their life as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of content on these platforms is short in duration. In fact, when it comes to advertising &lt;a href="https://blog.hubspot.com/marketing/how-long-should-videos-be-on-instagram-twitter-facebook-youtube"&gt;it's what the experts recommend&lt;/a&gt; --- short-form content of not more than a minute or so. When you're on social media flipping through these posts, you're training your brain to focus on a topic for minutes at a time before distracting it with another topic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have only one brain that's affected by what stimulates it. So when you're at work, it gradually becomes tougher to flesh out that presentation or write those lines of code without losing focus. It becomes hard to do "Deep Work". The kind of work that requires a long period of unbroken focus. The kind of work that has the most economic value. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3E7hkPZ-HTk"&gt;TEDx talk titled "Quit Social Media"&lt;/a&gt;, Dr. Cal Newport, Author and Associate Professor of Computer Science at Georgetown University, speaks about what the market values most in the 21st century: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you produce something that’s rare and valuable, the market will value that. What the market dismisses, for the most part, are activities that are easy to replicate and produce a small amount of value.
Well, social media use is the epitome of an easy to replicate activity that doesn’t produce a lot of value; it’s something that any six-year-old with a smartphone can do. By definition, the market is not going to give a lot of value to those behaviours. It’s instead going to reward the deep, concentrated work required to build real skills and to apply those skills to produce things — like a craftsman — that are rare and that are valuable.
To put it another way: if you can write an elegant algorithm, if you can write a legal brief that can change a case, if you can write a thousand words of prose that’s going to fixate a reader right to the end; if you can look at a sea of ambiguous data and apply statistics, and pull out insights that could transform a business strategy, if you can do these type of activities which require deep work, that produce outcomes that are rare and valuable, people will find you. You will be able to write your own ticket, and build the foundation of a meaningful and successful professional life, regardless of how many Instagram followers you have.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3E7hkPZ-HTk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pop The Bubble&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiment had made me a lot calmer and far less easily irritable than I was before. I sincerely believe that this was a direct product of not being outraged every other day by something on somebody's timeline. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content recommendation algorithms on any platform are quite predictable. Very few people know precisely how they work but we all know that if we watch a few videos on a certain topic, we can expect to be bombarded with similar videos in the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you tend to engage with content that irks you, &lt;a href="https://www.niemanlab.org/2019/03/one-year-in-facebooks-big-algorithm-change-has-spurred-an-angry-fox-news-dominated-and-very-engaged-news-feed/"&gt;the algorithms will keep serving you similar pieces of content&lt;/a&gt; because they want you to engage as much as possible, and you're going to be constantly outraged. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't meant to imply that you should avoid news and discussions like the plague. There are events, clear cases of injustice, that deserve public (or even worldwide) outrage and discourse. I just realized I have to be smart about what I spend my energy on. There's no point raging about everything that happens halfway around the world if my own house, network, community, and country isn't in order. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What frightens me the most is that you can stumble into an echo chamber on social media and not even know you're in one. It starts with a single piece of content, then something similar as the algorithm tries to keep you on the platform (hardly ever an opposing or balanced opinion because that might lead you away), and this goes on until much of your newsfeed is dedicated to the topic, and your ideologies and perceptions have shifted as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You've given a company, its algorithm, and those who influence it, control of your mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impressive but Superficial&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most rewarding outcome of the experiment was that my day-to-day interactions with people had begun to feel more genuine. By insisting on meetups and phone calls over likes and comments, I found it so much easier to open up to people and in turn rediscovered my love for having long conversations --- the ones that bounce from topic to topic and make the hours fly by. Since my focus had improved and I was less inclined to keep glancing at my phone, I was able to give people the attention they deserved and most importantly, enjoy their presence. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many interactions on social media are geared towards impressing people (I'm looking at you Instagram). We spend an awful lot of time on our online personality, thinking of the right thing to say or the best image to post, so we're perceived as how we'd like to be perceived --- strong, beautiful, funny, or intellectual. You certainly don't want people to think you're boring, dry and weak. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this doesn't lead to a genuine connection or friendship. Think about the people you call your closest friends. They haven't only seen your good and impressive side. They've also been angered by you. They've seen you cry. They've seen you act irrationally. They've been (accidentally) hurt by you and yet they've remained your friends because they've accepted your flaws and they chose to forgive your moments of weakness. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friendships are formed when we display our vulnerabilities to another person and trust that they will not take advantage of them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alain De Botton, a philosopher and the founder of the School of Life in a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=trKtqY_riZ8"&gt;recent Flow Session with Jason Silva&lt;/a&gt; said it best: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All genuine friendship begins the moment we take down the mask and we go “I’m suffering, this is difficult for me”. Every time that you trade with somebody a piece of information that puts you in a vulnerable position and departs from the script that we’re all given about what a successful life is, that’s friendship.
It’s such an irony we spend so much of our energy trying to impress others when really what we need is a sense of communion with others which is not based on impressing them. To impress another person is also to shut them off, it’s to close off our humanity from theirs. And so our success-oriented culture is fundamentally unlinked with our emotional aspirations to connect with other humans.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/trKtqY_riZ8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walking the Middle Path&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experiment ended two years ago and despite all of the above, it didn't end with me deleting my social media accounts. I certainly don't use it as often and I take very frequent long breaks but I don't preach abandoning it either. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is, after all, a great way to get in touch with old friends, help people in need, or find people with similar hobbies and interests. It has given the voiceless a platform, brought about awareness of important issues, and allows businesses to promote themselves and grow. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the answer to living with it is simple but very difficult to practice: &lt;em&gt;moderation&lt;/em&gt;. To help you with this, here's a list of things I've done and continue to do that you might find helpful: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App Timers&lt;/strong&gt; — Use &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.apps.wellbeing&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;gl=US"&gt;Digital Wellbeing for Android&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT208982"&gt;Screen Time for iOS&lt;/a&gt; to keep track of, and set daily limits on, your social media app usage. Believe me, it’s shocking the first time you see “You’ve used Instagram for 2 hours today” because you never notice your patterns until they’re laid out in front of you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long Passwords&lt;/strong&gt; — Change all your passwords to very long ones (with random letters, numbers, and symbols) and store them somewhere safe. Log out of the app or website once you’re done using it so you need to fish out that long password and carefully type it in each time you want to get back on. Making it cumbersome to log in will hopefully keep you away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Browser Versions&lt;/strong&gt; — Delete your social media apps and use their mobile browser versions instead. They’re clunkier and not as feature-rich. The poorer user experience is unlikely to keep you glued to it for long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose One&lt;/strong&gt; — Do you really need to be on Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, Snapchat, and TikTok at the same time? Choose one and delete the rest so you’re less inclined to switch between apps and spend more time on your phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;News Aggregator&lt;/strong&gt; — If you use social media for your daily dose of news, consider using a news aggregator such as &lt;a href="https://feedly.com/"&gt;Feedly&lt;/a&gt; instead. Whatever you choose, make sure it doesn’t have an endless newsfeed. There needs to be a clear end so you know when to stop and go about your day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Active Over Passive&lt;/strong&gt; — Passive consumption refers to consuming content recommended by a platform. Active consumption refers to going in search of content on a subject you want to know more about. Always opt for active. Get those gears working, think of something that interests you, and dive in. Sticking to one or a few topics will improve your focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dopamine Detox&lt;/strong&gt; — This is something I’m currently experimenting with after watching a video titled “How I tricked my brain to like doing hard things”. It’s based on the premise that because social media creates so much dopamine in our brain, our dopamine receptors now have very high tolerance levels. So just like alcoholics need a lot more alcohol to get drunk, we need to engage in more high dopamine activities to feel good. This results in us putting off low dopamine activities that are necessary for our development such as reading, writing, and learning. By spending a day a week or a few hours every day avoiding high dopamine activities and choosing to get bored instead, we can lower our dopamine tolerance and make reading or learning a lot more enjoyable. Boredom is good for us and makes us more creative and productive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9QiE-M1LrZk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck with your journey! I hope you can practice moderation, sharpen your focus, protect your thoughts, be proud of who you are, and connect better with those you love. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is only one aspect of our symbiotic relationship with digital technology which we're still largely trying to make sense of. The control of fire was mankind's greatest invention but as much as it cooks and welds, it also burns and harms. What is digital technology's equivalent of "don't put your hand into the fire"? How do we wield it to its greatest potential but not be overcome by it? How do we make sure it stays an untiring servant and never becomes a cruel master? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a lot more thinking to do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Stories"></category></entry><entry><title>What Do Digestion and Reading Have in Common?</title><link href="/digestion-and-reading.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-22T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-07-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-07-22:/digestion-and-reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This culture of optimization has given birth to a most ridiculous metric --- the number of books you can read in a period of time.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago I read an &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@JasonCMcBride/stop-optimizing-your-life-and-start-living-it-instead-884f3e0f4f7f"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on how "optimization" is creeping into every aspect of our lives. The article states: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everywhere from digital nomad gurus to the false prophets of productivity, we are taught how to optimize every aspect of our existence. You can find carefully scripted routines for your mornings, your sex life, and your bowel movements. There is no aspect of human life that you couldn’t be doing better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This culture of optimization has given birth to a most ridiculous metric --- the number of books you can read in a period of time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't lie, I'm especially bitter about this because I'm a slow reader. I like to take my time with the material. Let my mind wander and explore the other thoughts that pop into my head. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see reading as exploration akin to a walk in the woods and I'd rather enjoy the sights, smells and sounds than rush through the beauty only to boast about arriving at the end faster than somebody else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absurdity of the metric is that it's a terrible measure of knowledge. It's the equivalent of your self worth being measured with the number of likes you get on Facebook. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's because there's no deep learning in simply reading as many books as you can. To understand this better, let's think about something boring but generally understood --- digesting food. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you eat something delicious, you enjoy every scrumptious second of it on your taste buds. Your taste buds invoke a release of dopamine in your brain and you feel good. The chewed up food then moves down to your stomach and intestines where the process of digestion breaks it down into proteins, vitamins, carbohydrates and nutrients to be absorbed into your bloodstream, powering your body for as long as it can. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, your tongue may enjoy the taste of the food, but your body only benefits once its nutritional value is extracted through digestion and absorbed into your system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equivalent of digestion for reading is reflection. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflection involves re-reading, slow reading, pondering, playing with thoughts, and discussing what you've read with someone else. Much like digestion, reflection involves breaking things down and letting the rough-edged thoughts interact with the rest of what you know to form connections and thereby, a deeper understanding of the material you're reading. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's by taking the time to absorb these new ideas into your stream of knowledge, do you truly extract the intellectual value of the material. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an added advantage to reflection: time needed to reflect forces you to be more selective about what you read. The current culture around high book counts tend to involve including whatever is trending into your reading list but there are too many books whose contents aren't worthy of the hype they receive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the time needed to reflect and cut the "fat" from your reading list. Look through recommendations and reviews and be critical of what you choose to put into your mind. Read what you can hopefully get something out of (and that doesn't exclude good fiction that makes you think). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, don't turn reading for learning into a metric and attempt to optimize it. Learning occurs through reflection and reflection is a personal journey that cannot be quantified. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it may hurt to admit it as a data analyst, there are some things that just shouldn't be measured in numbers, and one of them is the joy of reading.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>How to Convince Someone You’re Smart</title><link href="/convince-someone-smart.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-28T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-02-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-02-28:/convince-someone-smart.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are broadly two ways you can convince someone you're knowledgeable about a particular field.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are broadly two ways you can convince someone you're knowledgeable about a particular field. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create confusion.&lt;/strong&gt; Usually done when you liberally use the field's jargon to the point where they don't know what you're talking about but the confidence in your voice leads them to assume you do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create understanding.&lt;/strong&gt; Boiling down the complexities of your field to a language they can understand and by doing so, igniting their awe and curiosity until the passion in your voice convinces them you're an expert. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While both methods may achieve your desired outcome of being seen as an intellectual in their eyes, only one of them leaves a lasting impression. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Knowledge is a process of piling up facts; wisdom lies in their simplification"
Martin H. Fischer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>Digital Mindfulness or the Act of Being Mindful of What You Consume Online</title><link href="/digital-mindfulness.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-16T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-02-16T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-02-16:/digital-mindfulness.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;20 pieces an hour across 6 hours is 120 pieces a day. Across a week that's 840. Across a month that's 3,650. And across a year that's 43,800.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many of us spend upwards of 6 hours online either for work or play. Let's assume that during these 6 hours we consume a minimum of 20 pieces of content an hour whether it's videos, photos, articles, statuses or comments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 pieces an hour across 6 hours is 120 pieces a day. Across a week that's 840. Across a month that's 3,650. And across a year that's 43,800. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's just based on my conservative estimate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, that's 43,800 times your mind can be influenced in various ways. Just as a movie can make you feel the pain or happiness of its main characters, every piece of content makes you feel something. They either delight you, inform you, frighten you, bore you, or anger you. Every piece releases some chemical in your brain and when it all snowballs together --- 43,800 times --- it shapes how you think. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want to lose weight, they tell you to be mindful of what you put in your body. They say, "great bodies are made in the kitchen, not at the gym". And when you follow their advice and eat healthy consistently, your body changes and reflects the goodness and richness of what you're feeding it. You become stronger and healthier. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very same applies to your mind. Every single thing you feed it, shapes it. If you feed it a stream of bite-sized, short-form content you will train your mind to pay attention and focus for only seconds or minutes at a time. If you feed it a stream of news that causes nothing but anger and fear, you will train your mind to see doubt and danger everywhere and with everyone. If you feed it a stream of content that causes nothing but amusement and joy, you will train your mind to be oblivious to the suffering of others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we see, is what we are. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have to accept that we cannot tear ourselves away from our screens. Not everyone can afford the luxury of selling their belongings and retreating into a forest to become a hermit. Our devices are now an extension of our being. They augment the way we entertain ourselves, build relationships and make a living. There are incredible advantages in their use. There's no running away from it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which leaves us with only one course of action --- extending the act of mindfulness to the digital realm. Being aware that what we do with our devices is affecting us in ways we may not know. Being conscious that too much of screen time, especially on applications engineered to instill addiction, can lead us down a spiral of anxiety and eventually, depression. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most of all, being selective with what we choose to put into our minds. Shying away from the ill-informed and superficial and gravitating towards the learned and enlightened. &lt;a href="https://ideas.ted.com/love-the-news-but-hate-clickbait-and-fluff-how-to-be-a-slower-and-more-thoughtful-news-consumer/"&gt;This article by Cal Newport on TED Ideas is a great place to start&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our thoughts shape our spaces and our spaces return the favor”
Steven Johnson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make every single one of those 43,800 pieces of content work in your favor. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2019/02/our-digital-lives-dont-need-to-make-us-unhappy-unhealthy-and-unwise"&gt;"Our Digital Lives Don't Need to Make Us Unhappy, Unhealthy, and Unwise" on the Harvard Business Review.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technology"></category></entry><entry><title>Rebranding The Seer</title><link href="/rebranding-the-seer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-07T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-11-07T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-11-07:/rebranding-the-seer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As science and technology progressed, no longer could the seers fool the wise man with talk of tapping into the unseen.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the days of old, there lived the seers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men and women who were gifted in the art of turning a tarot card, looking deep into a crystal ball, stirring wet tea leaves in a cup, or throwing twigs on the ground, to tap into the collective conscious of the Universe, look into the past, read the signs of the present, all in order to forecast the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who got it right and predicted the advancing of the enemy or the birth of a heir were rewarded with riches. But those who got it wrong were banished or paid with their lives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As science and technology progressed, no longer could the seers fool the wise man with talk of tapping into the unseen. No longer could the seers fool the people with proclamations of knowledge of all things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, the seers had to learn to tell different stories. Those that require years of study, specialization, and mastery of advanced tools, until confidence is gained in one's words. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the seers of old shed their titles and took on new ones --- Economist, Futurologist, Predictive Analyst, Machine Learning Specialist. They cast away their twigs and tarots, and instead learned the art of programming, mathematical modelling, and distributed computing, to tap into the hidden insights of data streams, leverage the learnings of the past, assess the actions of the present, all in order to forecast the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who get it right and predict the tumble of the market or the origins of a disease are rewarded with riches. But those who get it wrong are disregarded and cast aside, often paying with their pride.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>The Field Guide to Spotting Fake News in the Wild</title><link href="/field-guide-spotting-fake-news.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-08-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-08-10:/field-guide-spotting-fake-news.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;All you need is a simple blog/website, a Facebook page or Twitter account to distribute and promote your articles, and a bunch of pseudo-journalists blessed with a fake-news-writing ability.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fake news is a ridiculously profitable industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the margins are incredible! You don’t need a team of well-connected journalists spending too much time fact checking before publishing. You don’t need highly-paid editors ensuring compliance to basic morality and media ethics. And you certainly don’t need to bother with quality over quantity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All you need is a simple blog/website, a Facebook page or Twitter account to distribute and promote your articles, and a bunch of pseudo-journalists blessed with a fake-news-writing ability. An ability that is quite easy to develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010245.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010245.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone was once a child with a vivid imagination, right? So if you’ve still got a little bit of that imagination in you and you’ve lied &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; a few times in your life, then you too can take an event that actually took place, exaggerate the details, sprinkle a few lies here and there, misquote the sources, add more “credible sources”, and finally top it off with a sensationalistic Can-You-Believe-This-Happened headline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeat this for a couple of dozen articles and soon you’ll be attracting thousands of clicks, and thousands of eyeballs on those ads littered across your website. Each click will be a &lt;em&gt;cha-ching&lt;/em&gt; in your bank account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conning Generations of Internet Users&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it sounds absolutely absurd and it should be very simple to see right through a piece of fake news for what it really is, it’s insane how many of us are so easily conned into believing something that just isn’t true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, does your mom or dad use an instant messaging app like WhatsApp? If so, go take a look (with permission of course) at what they’re sharing and what they’re receiving from your aunties and uncles. I bet you that somewhere in the cluster of messages there’ll be an old wives’ tale being passed off as a revolutionary medical breakthrough that doctors despise because it means patients don’t have to be treated by them anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we can forgive our older generation though, because many of them (especially in developing countries) may be new to the room-full-of-cobwebs that we call the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do we excuse the hundreds of thousands of digital natives of our generation and the generations after us who grew up well aware of the presence of misinformation online and yet are still fooled by blatant nonsense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What ever happened to the old saying, “&lt;em&gt;Don’t believe everything you read online&lt;/em&gt;”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fake News = Unnecessary Outbursts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your older cousin trying to rub a baked potato on your face as a cure for your acne because a video on www.acnegoneinaday.zimbabwe told her to do so, should be the least of your worries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake news, created with an agenda, can spread like wildfire, drastically shifting perceptions, worsening tensions between communities, races, and religions, and possibly even resulting in outrage and violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just recently in India, &lt;a href="http://indianexpress.com/article/india/west-bengal-communal-violence-one-arrested-for-sharing-fake-image-and-inciting-passion-4742488/"&gt;a still image from a Hindi movie of a man forcibly pulling a woman’s saree&lt;/a&gt; made its rounds on social media after it was falsely described as a picture of a Muslim man harassing a Hindu woman. A &lt;a href="http://www.hindustantimes.com/kolkata/bjp-it-cell-secretary-arrested-in-asansol-for-posting-fake-video-on-social-media/story-GSLBmA1746fQlk5YupJrgI.html"&gt;video of unknown origin&lt;/a&gt; falsely described as depicting two Muslim police officers beating up a Hindu man went viral as well. An old image from 2002 of the riots in Gujarat was falsely described as a photograph taken during the &lt;a href="http://www.firstpost.com/india/watch-west-bengal-communal-riots-decoding-the-factors-behind-the-violence-spread-across-many-districts-3781759.html"&gt;recent riots in West Bengal&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://indianexpress.com/article/india/west-bengal-communal-violence-bjp-spokesperson-nupur-sharma-shares-2002-gujarat-riots-image-calls-for-protest-at-jantar-mantar-4742737/"&gt;used as a propaganda piece by politicians to call for more protests&lt;/a&gt;. Each piece of fake news intensified communal tension in the already unstable West Bengal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year a photo of Syrian children who died during a chemical attack was &lt;a href="https://www.morningnewsusa.com/thailand-child-organ-trafficking-photo-facts-to-know-23128278.html"&gt;falsely described by fake news websites&lt;/a&gt; as a photo of children who had had their organs harvested by Thai kidnappers and organ traffickers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the story about Donald Trump signing a $110 billion arms deal with Saudi Arabia on his recent visit to the Middle East? Even mainstream news outlets carried the story. &lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2017/05/20/us-saudi-arabia-seal-weapons-deal-worth-nearly-110-billion-as-trump-begins-visit.html"&gt;CNBC&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/donald-trump-arms-deal-saudi-arabia-110-billion-911-terrorism-international-law-war-crimes-a7747076.html"&gt;The Independent&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://thehill.com/homenews/administration/334368-trump-to-sign-110b-defense-deal-with-saudi-arabia"&gt;The Hill&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2017/05/saudi-arabia-sign-arms-deals-worth-110bn-170520141943494.html"&gt;Al Jazeera.&lt;/a&gt; Probably because Sean Spicer, the (former) White House Press Secretary, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/presssec/status/865937500610723841?lang=en"&gt;announced it&lt;/a&gt;. However, upon closer examination, &lt;a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/markaz/2017/06/05/the-110-billion-arms-deal-to-saudi-arabia-is-fake-news/"&gt;a researcher at Brookings Institute discovered that there is no deal&lt;/a&gt;; there are only letters of interest and intent. The $110 billion arms deal story that led to so much outrage is allegedly a piece of fake news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010253.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010253.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably a more harder-to-detect example of fake news. It took a seasoned researcher with contacts in the arms industry to detect it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So do we, the average joes, stand a chance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not when it comes to complex and specific matters such as international arms agreements but in many other cases, yes. Just like the best antivirus for your computer is your common sense (&lt;em&gt;don’t click on any of those suspicious links!)&lt;/em&gt;, the best tool to use when determining the validity of a story is your own brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, as netizens with the power to share to thousands who may go on to share to millions, you have a great responsibility to ensure that what you’re sharing is 100% accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s even 0.0001% short of 100%, you should think twice about clicking that share button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to turn foolish trust into educated skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summon Your Inner Robot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t let your emotions take advantage of you when you’re consuming a piece of content. Much of the news today is created to elicit shock, anger, frustration or sadness, sometimes just by the headline itself. It’s the oldest trick in the book to drive traffic to a website to earn more ad dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So once you’ve read, watched, or listened to something, don’t give in to your finger just twitching to forward it to someone else. Turn on the rational part of your brain and walk that piece of content through this list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) Does the web address (URL) seem very similar to the web address of an established news provider?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it bbc.co.uk or bbbc.co.uk? Is it dailymirror.lk or dailymiror.lk? Is it cnn.com or cnn.co?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010259.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010259.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_fake_news_websites"&gt;latter in any of the above cases&lt;/a&gt;, then your internal fake news detection device should be dinging. Especially if the design of the fake news website is very similar (in terms of the logo, colours, layout or font) to the website of the established news provider it’s trying to impersonate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Check the sources and then double-check the sources!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the content piece contain any sources or references? If not, be suspicious. If it states “anonymous sources have revealed…”, be suspicious anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the item-in-question has quoted someone in a particular position at a particular institution, use Google to check if that person exists, if that position exists and if that institution exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if all of the above exists, it won’t hurt to look for an official statement or press release by that person or institution. It is possible that their statements have been misquoted or taken out of context to make the news piece more sensational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) Have any mainstream media outlets covered the story yet?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capture the gist of the video or article in as few words as possible and Google it. See if any credible mainstream media outlets (either internationally or locally) have covered the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large number of mainstream outlets carrying the story is a good sign. Although be warned, the details of the story may be very different to what you’ve seen on non-mainstream media. So it’ll be wise to go beyond the headline to reading the article or watching the video before jumping to any conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) In the case of a questionable photograph, use Google’s reverse image search.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a news piece is centered around a photograph, then use Google’s reverse image search to see if the photo is really what the caption associated with it makes it seem to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either download the photo or copy the URL of the photo by right-clicking it and selecting “Copy image address”. Then head over to images.google.com, click the little camera icon which will enable reverse image search and upload the image or paste the URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010307.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010307.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re using Google Chrome, you can simply right-click on an image and select “Search Google for image.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010313.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010313.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the results show the same photograph being used in an unrelated context, then you have every reason to be suspicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Check with the veteran warriors against fake news — Snopes and Hoax-Slayer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snopes.com and hoax-slayer.com have been engaged in the battle against old wives’ tales, internet scams, and fake news since the rise of the internet. They use meticulous research to determine if a story is entirely true, entirely false or contains some truth to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to search through Snopes or Hoax-Slayer for a story you want to verify is by copying a line from the article (or summarizing the gist of the video), pasting it on the Google search bar, and adding “snopes” or “hoax-slayer” after it before hitting the search button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6) What’s the other content like?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s a website, take a look at some of the other content pieces. If it’s a YouTube channel, take a look at some of the other videos. If it’s a Twitter account, take a look at some of the other tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010319.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010319.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any of the other content seems overly sensational, has misleading headlines, or are completely unsubstantiated, then let your doubts arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7) Who has written the article and what else has s/he written?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the by-line! It’s either right after the headline or at the bottom of the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google the name to see if that person actually exists. Most of the time you can also click on the person’s name to see a list of articles s/he has contributed to the website. If any of them seem fishy to you, by a rule of thumb, I would advise against believing anything s/he has to say without proper evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absence of a by-line doesn’t always mean the news item is fake. The BBC for instance doesn’t have a by-line on their online articles. However the BBC is a world renowned media organization with a long-standing history of a high degree of credibility. Something many non-mainstream media outlets don’t possess. So the absence of a by-line on the website of a non-mainstream outlet should raise your suspicions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8) Don’t be &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know what &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt; does? He reads only the headline and creates his own biased story in his head. He doesn’t know that most media outlets use sensational headlines to attract clicks so he doesn’t bother reading the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That guy&lt;/em&gt; also doesn’t check the date of the article. He’ll share an old story and act like it just happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That guy&lt;/em&gt; takes everything too seriously. He doesn’t know how to tell satirical articles from serious articles. A &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt; is probably a heckler at a stand-up comedy show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If after all of this, you’re &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; not sure if a story is true or false, then check with a friend. Ideally a friend who doesn’t wear a tinfoil hat and believe every conspiracy theory in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And remember, you should always check to see if a news item is fake regardless of who shared it with you, how educated they are, and what they do. It doesn’t matter if it’s your uncle who’s a nuclear scientist; even nuclear scientists can give in to their emotions and share without fact-checking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop the Avalanche&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This list is definitely not fool-proof. It’s possible that a piece of content can pass through every test and still end up being fake. But it does pay to squint your eyes, move your head to the side and be skeptical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to hold our media outlets to a higher standard, even the ones we consider mainstream. We need to demand evidence, credible sources, and the entire unbiased picture, while taking responsibility for reading the entire story, comprehending it, and not letting our personal biases or prejudices get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is our collective responsibility to prevent the spread of fake news and in turn prevent the outbursts that fake news has a tendency to generate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the brightest minds in &lt;a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/gadgets-and-tech/news/facebook-fake-news-feature-uk-election-2017-a7720506.html"&gt;social media&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2017/apr/25/google-launches-major-offensive-against-fake-news"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; continue to tackle this problem with improved algorithms, new tools, and stricter regulations, they still have a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake news and its creators will always find a way to wriggle in, but we can stop giving them the pedestal that they do not deserve by thinking twice before we click “Share”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, it only takes one snowflake to start an avalanche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other References&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ifla.org/publications/node/11174"&gt;How to Spot Fake News&lt;/a&gt; (International Federation of Library Associations and Institutions, 2017)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technology"></category></entry></feed>