<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jaro Says - Reflections</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/reflections.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated><subtitle>Reflections, Technology, Analytics, and Stories</subtitle><entry><title>Our Worship Has Come Full Circle</title><link href="/worship-full-circle.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-06T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-05-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-05-06:/worship-full-circle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If the forests were lit ablaze during a thunderstorm, it's because we had angered the thunder gods.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In ancient times, objects, events, and beings guided our worship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient Objects&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were ancestral carvings made of clay, stone or wood. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were gigantic trees, mountains, and boulders whose presence and sight struck us in awe. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were natural, seemingly otherworldly formations -- such as gems and crystals -- discovered in the earth or its cavities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worshipped these objects for they had some unexplainable effect on us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient Events&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the forests were lit ablaze during a thunderstorm, it's because we had angered the thunder gods.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an earthquake destroyed our village, it was a punishment inflicted by the gods of the land.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If rain did not fall and we could not quench our thirst, the water gods were testing our faith. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We felt powerless in the midst of these events, so we cried out to those that determined them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancient Beings&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the village shaman's concoctions cured our ailing children, she was gifted our most treasured possessions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the local soothsayer, by an absolute stroke of luck, predicted an eclipse, he was determined to be a supernatural being. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a tribal leader was victorious in conquest over and over again, he was branded a god of war, and a king of kings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beings that successfully challenged the odds, for better or worse, were made worthy of our worship. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then came the beliefs in the unseen, the untouched, and the unexperienced. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The religions. The faiths. The philosophies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These beliefs were compelling. They delighted those of us who believed in one and angered those of us that believed in another. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wars were waged. Lives were lost. Voices were silenced and stories forgotten.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, only some beliefs remained. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;History repeats itself.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although we call ourselves believers of some faith, we spend most of our time, again guiding our worship through objects, events, and beings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Objects&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are mansions that sit atop hills overlooking affluent neighbourhoods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are sleek vehicles with curves that rival a voluptuous female form. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are mineral-infused devices that we carry in our pockets and call our second brain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worship these objects for they have some unexplainable effect on us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Events&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the economy crashes and millions lose their jobs, it\'s because the very foundations of our systems were shaken too hard. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the military rises in revolution and ousts our democratically appointed leaders, it\'s a message violently sent by an imperialist collective. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If famine breaks out in one country despite the abundance of food in another, it\'s a result of wilful ignorance and wilful inaction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We feel powerless in the midst of these events, so we cry out to those that determine them. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Beings&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a business leader creates an offering to service a need we never knew we had, she is handed millions of our dollars. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When charismatic but incapable individuals arise to challenge qualified incumbents who cannot speak to the hearts of the people, they are awarded the highest positions of power. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an individual offers people a spiritual or emotional respite from the monotony of the unending rat race, she is branded a philosopher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beings that successfully challenged the odds, for better or worse, were made worthy of our worship.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>More Like Beau: Why I’m Looking For Stories in My Daily Life</title><link href="/more-like-beau.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-08-18:/more-like-beau.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, my life started feeling rather ordinary. I woke up, I worked, I exercised, I slept, I repeated. There was no adventure, there was no surprise around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I live on my phone and my laptop more than I live in the world. I think that that's been true for most of us during this pandemic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've been robbed of our opportunity to travel, hike, camp, be intimate, go out for coffee, try new food, make new friends, and form stronger bonds with existing ones. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-3-576x1024.jpeg" src="/images/image-3-576x1024.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure you can do the last one on Zoom but a conversation in person &lt;em&gt;just hits different.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my life started feeling rather ordinary. I woke up, I worked, I exercised, I slept, I repeated. There was no adventure, there was no surprise around the corner, and with these constant (but necessary) lockdowns there was no more looking forward to a night out or a holiday in the countryside. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What'd I do because I couldn't get my adventure fix? I turned to the virtual world. I began inhaling videos and articles about how other people live their lives in a variety of exciting ways. This sea of online personalities with their jaw-dropping feats, interesting jobs, and hilarious quirks was my respite: my break away from the monotony of daily life. For a moment, all I lived to do was experience somebody else's story. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I discovered Beau Miles. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beau isn't your typical Youtuber. He doesn't upload very often. He doesn't have millions of subscribers (although he really ought to). His videos aren't overly-edited barrages of clips with a screaming narrator. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beau is a Professor of Adventure Education at Monash University, Australia. He's got a doctorate in the subject! He lives on a farm with his wife and kid. He collects junk (mostly wood) by the side of the road and uses his carpentry skills to breathe life into them. Oh, and he runs...a lot. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-5 1.png" src="/images/image-5 1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first stumbled upon his channel, I started with his older content. The man has paddled 2000km in a canoe around the southern tip of Africa! Over time, however, his adventures began taking place in and around his neighbourhood. Like the time he ran a mile every hour and spent every minute in-between getting through a lengthy to-do list. Or the time he spent a night on a 100-year old Gum tree right outside his farm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he began to embrace spending time in and around his home, his content began changing my perspective towards my locked-down life. See, Beau wasn't "going" on adventures anymore, he was "finding" them. He would look at something ordinary, like the remnants of an abandoned railroad, and then decide to celebrate its history by running its length dressed as a train conductor holding a coal shovel. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rxCghemtjjM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, 43km isn't really within the radius of a "neighbourhood" but Australia is a massive place so their neighbourhoods are much bigger than ours &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wondered, to make my life more interesting, do I just need to pay more attention to what's around me? Unglue my face from the black mirror and appreciate an environment I have for so long ignored in favour of the thrills of the internet? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of "perception" is the meaning you assign to your sensory input. In other words, it's the internal story that you write in your mind whenever you experience something. The better your perception, the more meaningful your experiences are, and by extension, your stories become more interesting and perhaps, extraordinary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same vein, a human life is simply a collection of stories written every day. When each day's chapter begins to sound the same you feel like chucking the book out the window. But when you start sharpening your perception: spending more time observing and reflecting than drowning out your senses with audio and video, you begin to realize that even the seemingly mundane has something of interest to offer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beau Miles and his wacky adventures didn't lead me to this realization. He planted the seed of course, but the several herniated discs in my spine watered it. After a terrible episode of pain that left me bedridden for a few days, my physiotherapist suggested a daily walk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, the walks were simply a necessity. I turned on a podcast, made my way around my neighbourhood, and resumed whatever I was up to at home. Then, in the spirit of "What Would Beau Do", I started paying more attention to the people and things around me on my walks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-4.jpeg" src="/images/image-4.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started noticing things about my neighbourhood that have somehow escaped me for years. Like the fact that there's a quaint little coffee shop near my house (which I'll visit once COVID eases again) or the fact that between every set of nice properties there are run-down houses. The rich and the poor living side-by-side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A distant neighbour also has two humongous dogs that bark their guts out every time I walk past them. They can't see it through my mask, but I'm pretty sure they can smell my fear. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-5.jpeg" src="/images/image-5.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the most interesting to observe are the people. I don't know many of these people, especially the ones further away from home. I can only imagine what they must be thinking or going through, but often their body language speaks volumes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are the forlorn faces staring out of shop windows, perhaps wondering if their tills will ever weigh heavy again. There are the worried eyes peering above double-masks with long strides and a quick pace, perhaps rushing home to avoid a disease that seems to lurk around every corner. There are the labourers, like the garage mechanic twisting a wrench under a car, fixing it up perhaps for some customer's hopeful wish for a road trip in the near future. And then, on the other end of the spectrum, we have the arrogant, masking nothing but their necks and going about their lives unbothered by the pandemic. Perhaps the statistics haven't turned to names for them yet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My back pain isn't the only reason I walk anymore. It's become a therapeutic experience. I adjust my route around my neighbourhood every once in a while for a change of scenery but the process remains the same. Walk, observe, and look for stories. I'm not looking to spin a long yarn, I'm just in search of little internal realizations that I can add to my life's story so that no two chapters sound the same. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working on my perception has had a tremendous impact on my perspective. When you tell yourself stories of how difficult the lives around you seem to be, you feel grateful for what you have. When you realize you're walking for leisure while others walk for their livelihood, you feel thankful for a job you can do from home. When you actually get out of the house and use your neck muscles and your eyeballs, you realize your neighbourhood has so much more to offer than you thought. And when you add it all up, life won't seem so ordinary after all. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I set off on my walk a little too late in the evening, walked down a dimly lit road and accidentally invaded a dog's personal space. After I finished getting away from him, I got caught in a sudden storm. To add insult to my drenched injury, I was splashed by a car. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'm no Beau Miles, but that's as much adventure as I've had in the past few months and I'll take it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>Lessons In Love and Resilience From My Grandmother</title><link href="/lessons-in-love-resilience-grandmother.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-31T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-07-31T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-07-31:/lessons-in-love-resilience-grandmother.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some people wear these moments of darkness like a cloak, concealed in the thoughts of the past and what could have been. But Neney lit candles in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-1-1024x1024.png" src="/images/image-1-1024x1024.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime during the early part of the year, at the end of a regular weekend visit, I sat down next to my &lt;em&gt;Neney&lt;/em&gt; (grandmother) to say goodbye. She always hated it when we left her, even when we promised we would return the next day or the next weekend. She usually protested with "don't go, stay here with me" or "why do you need to leave", but this time was different. This time, she grabbed my hand and said "stay". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was something in the way she firmly held my hand that moved me. She had been bedridden for some time now and didn't have a lot of energy throughout the day, so this little act was far more taxing for her than it would be for you or me. She didn't say anything. She just closed her eyes and enjoyed a few more moments of being together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-1.jpeg" src="/images/image-1.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My grandmother had a difficult life. She wasn't born into wealth and she dropped out of school after eighth grade. She went hungry to feed her children. She lost her husband far too early. She lost two children, when they were toddlers. She tragically lost another child, more recently and very suddenly. No parent should ever have to bury a child, much less three. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people wear these moments of darkness like a cloak, concealed in the thoughts of the past and what could have been. But Neney lit candles in the dark. From grief, she drew greater love for her family. She expressed her love by turning every interaction, no matter how brief, into an occasion. You couldn't walk away from her without your belly full and without having engaged in a long conversation, often packed with as many questions as an episode of Larry King Live. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our family used to joke about the number of questions she would ask. She was highly inquisitive so she wanted to know everything about you, what you were up to, and how you were feeling. She's probably the reason I have the endurance to get through long exams and job interviews. Looking back, I've come to understand that this was her subtle way of extending your stay, of absorbing your presence, and of making sure you were happy. Having realized the bitter truth of life's impermanence, her job was to make sure you felt loved and she was always on the clock. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-2.png" src="/images/image-2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-3 1.png" src="/images/image-3 1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever we spoke of problems or trouble, she leaned on her philosophy of life, brilliantly summed up in four jovial words --- "what is that so?" Posed as a question, it really made you think about the gravity of your problem and whether you were spending far too much time ruminating over something that just wouldn't matter in the grand scheme of things. This was her wonderful way of switching on your positive thinking. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neney loved creativity in all its forms. She was a voracious reader who would mouth the words silently to herself as she read (I didn't realize I had picked that up from her until I was a teenager). She loved films, music, and social events. She also encouraged us to be creative. She often asked me to give a speech at her birthday, and always demanded a written copy of the speech afterwards. Similarly, after any event, she absolutely needed to get her hands on the photos taken. Her appreciation for creativity made her a collector of family memorabilia and she made sure to revisit them often. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-2.jpeg" src="/images/image-2.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-4 1.png" src="/images/image-4 1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that was really the extent of her demands. Despite giving so much of her time, attention, and energy, she desired very little in return. That's because she never wanted to be a burden. You could see it in her face when she wasn't able to get out of bed more often. She yearned to have more energy, she yearned to be in the center of the crowd, she yearned to be the caretaker. So even though her body started giving way, she never let her mind go. She still wanted to be present, she still wanted to recognize and converse. To give you something in return for the trouble you had taken to come see her. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ezmaline Zunaiha Jaro died during the Holy Month of Ramadan on the 25th of April 2021 at 91 years of age. She was very religious, prayed five times a day, and would've wanted a traditional Muslim burial. Thanks to several members of the family, we were able to give her that, despite the pandemic. God also blessed her, for one last time, in another special way. She had been waiting a year to see her youngest son, and when she passed away, it was in his arms. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neney would've been 92 on the 2nd of August 2021. I know she would want us to celebrate her life and not dwell on our loss. And if she were around and saw any of us being sad for too long, I'd expect she'd give us a big hug and say "what is that so?" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1_5hH6T6Nghg44MAvADZ8tUA.jpg" src="/images/1_5hH6T6Nghg44MAvADZ8tUA.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>What Do Digestion and Reading Have in Common?</title><link href="/digestion-and-reading.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-22T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-07-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-07-22:/digestion-and-reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This culture of optimization has given birth to a most ridiculous metric --- the number of books you can read in a period of time.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago I read an &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@JasonCMcBride/stop-optimizing-your-life-and-start-living-it-instead-884f3e0f4f7f"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on how "optimization" is creeping into every aspect of our lives. The article states: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everywhere from digital nomad gurus to the false prophets of productivity, we are taught how to optimize every aspect of our existence. You can find carefully scripted routines for your mornings, your sex life, and your bowel movements. There is no aspect of human life that you couldn’t be doing better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This culture of optimization has given birth to a most ridiculous metric --- the number of books you can read in a period of time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't lie, I'm especially bitter about this because I'm a slow reader. I like to take my time with the material. Let my mind wander and explore the other thoughts that pop into my head. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see reading as exploration akin to a walk in the woods and I'd rather enjoy the sights, smells and sounds than rush through the beauty only to boast about arriving at the end faster than somebody else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absurdity of the metric is that it's a terrible measure of knowledge. It's the equivalent of your self worth being measured with the number of likes you get on Facebook. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's because there's no deep learning in simply reading as many books as you can. To understand this better, let's think about something boring but generally understood --- digesting food. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you eat something delicious, you enjoy every scrumptious second of it on your taste buds. Your taste buds invoke a release of dopamine in your brain and you feel good. The chewed up food then moves down to your stomach and intestines where the process of digestion breaks it down into proteins, vitamins, carbohydrates and nutrients to be absorbed into your bloodstream, powering your body for as long as it can. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, your tongue may enjoy the taste of the food, but your body only benefits once its nutritional value is extracted through digestion and absorbed into your system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equivalent of digestion for reading is reflection. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflection involves re-reading, slow reading, pondering, playing with thoughts, and discussing what you've read with someone else. Much like digestion, reflection involves breaking things down and letting the rough-edged thoughts interact with the rest of what you know to form connections and thereby, a deeper understanding of the material you're reading. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's by taking the time to absorb these new ideas into your stream of knowledge, do you truly extract the intellectual value of the material. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an added advantage to reflection: time needed to reflect forces you to be more selective about what you read. The current culture around high book counts tend to involve including whatever is trending into your reading list but there are too many books whose contents aren't worthy of the hype they receive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the time needed to reflect and cut the "fat" from your reading list. Look through recommendations and reviews and be critical of what you choose to put into your mind. Read what you can hopefully get something out of (and that doesn't exclude good fiction that makes you think). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, don't turn reading for learning into a metric and attempt to optimize it. Learning occurs through reflection and reflection is a personal journey that cannot be quantified. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it may hurt to admit it as a data analyst, there are some things that just shouldn't be measured in numbers, and one of them is the joy of reading.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>How to Convince Someone You’re Smart</title><link href="/convince-someone-smart.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-28T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-02-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-02-28:/convince-someone-smart.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are broadly two ways you can convince someone you're knowledgeable about a particular field.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are broadly two ways you can convince someone you're knowledgeable about a particular field. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create confusion.&lt;/strong&gt; Usually done when you liberally use the field's jargon to the point where they don't know what you're talking about but the confidence in your voice leads them to assume you do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create understanding.&lt;/strong&gt; Boiling down the complexities of your field to a language they can understand and by doing so, igniting their awe and curiosity until the passion in your voice convinces them you're an expert. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While both methods may achieve your desired outcome of being seen as an intellectual in their eyes, only one of them leaves a lasting impression. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Knowledge is a process of piling up facts; wisdom lies in their simplification"
Martin H. Fischer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry><entry><title>Rebranding The Seer</title><link href="/rebranding-the-seer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-07T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-11-07T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-11-07:/rebranding-the-seer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As science and technology progressed, no longer could the seers fool the wise man with talk of tapping into the unseen.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the days of old, there lived the seers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Men and women who were gifted in the art of turning a tarot card, looking deep into a crystal ball, stirring wet tea leaves in a cup, or throwing twigs on the ground, to tap into the collective conscious of the Universe, look into the past, read the signs of the present, all in order to forecast the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who got it right and predicted the advancing of the enemy or the birth of a heir were rewarded with riches. But those who got it wrong were banished or paid with their lives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As science and technology progressed, no longer could the seers fool the wise man with talk of tapping into the unseen. No longer could the seers fool the people with proclamations of knowledge of all things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, the seers had to learn to tell different stories. Those that require years of study, specialization, and mastery of advanced tools, until confidence is gained in one's words. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so the seers of old shed their titles and took on new ones --- Economist, Futurologist, Predictive Analyst, Machine Learning Specialist. They cast away their twigs and tarots, and instead learned the art of programming, mathematical modelling, and distributed computing, to tap into the hidden insights of data streams, leverage the learnings of the past, assess the actions of the present, all in order to forecast the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who get it right and predict the tumble of the market or the origins of a disease are rewarded with riches. But those who get it wrong are disregarded and cast aside, often paying with their pride.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflections"></category></entry></feed>