<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jaro Says - Self-Promoting</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/self-promoting.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+08:00</updated><subtitle>Reflections, Technology, Analytics, and Stories</subtitle><entry><title>Webinar Transcript: What Does a Data Scientist Do in the Working World?</title><link href="/webinar-data-scientist-real-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-01T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-08-01:/webinar-data-scientist-real-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is a raw transcript of my webinar for the students of the Royal Institute School on behalf of the school’s Career Guidance Unit.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is a raw transcript of my webinar for the students of the Royal Institute School on behalf of the school\'s Career Guidance Unit.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone and thank you for that introduction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m aware that the majority of the audience today is O-Level and A-Level students so I’m going to do my very best to keep things simple but informative and hopefully to keep you somewhat entertained as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot that I can talk about on this topic but what I’ll be doing today is, instead of diving deep into one or two specific examples, I’ll give you a few high-level ways of thinking about data science that you can then use to figure out how you can carve out a role for yourself as a professional with data science skills in the business world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to ask questions throughout the webinar, drop them in the chat, and I’ll get to them at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005550.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005550.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this webinar is on the working world, I figured let’s start with why I work in data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent my late teenage years and my early 20s doing a lot of exploration. I worked in market research, I worked in radio, I worked as a voiceover artist, I was an entrepreneur, a digital marketer, a blogger, a salesman, and the whole aim of this mess of affairs and roles, at least in my mind, was to get exposure to as many different problems as possible, so that I could figure out which ones fascinated me enough that I would want to work on it for the rest of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I had some specific criteria for what problems are fascinating to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to wear many different hats or work in many different roles while solving the problem. In other words, I did not want any two days to be the same. I did not want to live a life of monotony where you do the same thing every single day. I wanted the freedom and flexibility to be able to shift into another role that’s different enough to engage me but still relevant to my experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted the problems to require the use of both sides of my brain — the creative right and the analytical left. I knew that the field that would fascinate me would be that which requires using both science and art to solve its problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And finally, and perhaps, most importantly, I wanted to work on problems that are fascinating to everyone, not just to those working in the field. I didn’t want people to turn around and walk away when I start talking to them about what I do. I wanted them to be as fascinated as I am about the amount of potential and possibilities that could be unlocked with solving these problems. Because in all honesty, that’s where the money is. In our digital world, the money is where everyone’s attention is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this led to me stumbling upon data science and data analytics that checked all of this criteria. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005556.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005556.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just so we’re all on the same page because I know there may be students here who don’t exactly know what data science is: very simply put, data science involves extracting insights from raw data, for example patterns and trends, to be used for decision making either by people or by machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you’ve ever bought anything from any major e-commerce store like Amazon or Daraz, you would’ve seen a section titled “customers who were interested in this product, also bought these other products”, so if you were interested in buying a bicycle of a certain premium brand you’d see premium bike seat covers or a high-end bike lock in the recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s happening behind the scenes is that a machine is looking over very large volumes of transaction data, finding patterns in what customers purchase together, and then automatically recommending related products that you might find helpful. And it’s doing this because the company obviously wants you to buy more so they can make as much money from you as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005604.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005604.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s an example of what you can achieve with data science but the really neat thing about data science is that it is so broad it cuts across every single function of an organization and every single industry and appeals to different types of people with different skillsets and different personalities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now these are three things I want to expand on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005609.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005609.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the first – cutting across every function and several industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every business in the world is made up of teams of people with certain roles and responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have management (the CEOs, COOs, CFOs, the strategists and planners) who are responsible for steering the ship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have sales and marketing which are responsible for generating business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have finance that’s responsible for ensuring the company stays afloat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have operations or engineering or manufacturing that’s responsible for designing, creating, and delivering products or services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have legal whose job is to ensure the company isn’t breaking any laws or putting itself at risk of being sued.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have HR who needs to make sure there are enough people with the right skills employed by the company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have customer service that needs to help customers with their problems and ensure they’re happy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have IT which needs to make sure all the systems are kept alive and everyone has the tools they need to do their jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could keep going but these are largely the main functions of most organizations and data science is extremely useful and relevant to every single one of these functions. Let me give you some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, management could figure out which regions or markets are the most profitable to expand into because those are really expensive decisions where you can’t afford to make a mistake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, the marketing team can test thousands of different types of advertisements and then spend significantly more on the ones that customers respond to the best thereby maximizing the performance of their campaign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, the finance team can predict if the company is on its way to achieving its revenue and profit targets for the quarter and alert management if it’s not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, the operations team can predict how many orders the company might get in the near future so that they can make sure there are enough people, machines, and warehouse space ready to meet the demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, the legal team can very quickly find past cases similar to whatever legal case they’re facing right now so they spend less time researching and more time strategizing and planning on how to win.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, HR can automatically reduce the 1000s of CVs they’ve gotten for a certain role to just the top 10 that meets all the criteria required for the role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using data science, customer service can proactively reach out to customers who’ve recently bought but are not using their product so they can ensure they don’t regret their purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And using data science, IT can monitor the usage of systems so they can get rid of systems that aren’t in use or shut them down and save some money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this means for data scientists is that you have a buffet of work to choose from. You could be a generalist and work across all these functions or you could be a specialist in, for example marketing analytics or operational analytics, or you could keep jumping around whenever you get bored of one thing. That’s the beauty of data science, there are so many applications within the business world and beyond it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My advice: you’re probably already interested in one of these things, learn it and then pair it with knowledge of data science. Even if you don’t end up being called a data scientist, possessing data science skills along with expertise in a certain domain will put you a notch above the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005615.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005615.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve looked at a range of functions and how data science cuts across all of it. It’s easy to imagine how data science cuts across various industries too. Instead of generic examples across a ton of different industries or the stuff you’ve probably heard about like self-driving cars and highly targeted advertising, I’d like to talk about 3 slightly unorthodox uses of data science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first is farm analytics. This is where data science is used to better manage farms. Think of drones carrying cameras using computer vision to keep track of herds of sheep and cows on a very large farm. Think of sensors being used below and above the land to continuously measure the health of soil and crops and then automatically trigger water and fertilizer dispensers if needed. A lot of this stuff saves farmers a lot of time and labour and it helps them focus on growing more nutritious crops at cheaper prices that eventually benefit all of us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second is sports analytics and I’m going to use Formula 1 as an example. Formula 1 cars have over 300 sensors that generate nearly 1.5 million data points per second. That’s a lot of data and so they need to use high performance computing solutions to crunch all those numbers and put it in formats and visualizations that the engineers and drivers can easily understand. These engineers and drivers then use this information to make changes to the configuration of the car or the drivers use the information to see which parts of the track they need to improve on, for example, on which parts they’re braking too much for or too little for. Because even if they can shave off half a second in their performance, in Formula 1 that can mean the difference between 10th place and 1st place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third is entertainment analytics. There are fascinating case studies about how movie studios are using computer vision to continuously monitor the emotions and engagement of an audience during a test screening of a movie. The program can tell when people are laughing, interested, or just bored based on their facial expressions and body language. So, for example, if the program discovers that nobody laughed after a joke in the movie, the scriptwriters can rewrite that part of the movie and re-test it. That way using data science movie studios can create movies that are highly entertaining from start to finish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this is one way of looking at what you could do as a data scientist in the working world. There is another and that takes me back to the other point I wanted to expand on — appealing to different types of people with different skillsets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005624.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005624.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at a typical data science workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We always start with a question we want to answer or a problem we want to solve. For example, which of our customers should we focus on? We have 100,000 but we want to identify the ones that we should spend the most time with and who’ll generate the highest return for our business. Remember companies don’t have infinite resources, there’s only a set amount of money and time you can spend and you need to prioritize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we need to collect data relevant to the question. We need to extract all our customer data from all the systems we’re using in this company and we need to figure out how to put it all together so we’re working with datasets that give us a complete picture of who our customers are and how they’ve interacted with our business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we need to understand and explore this data. Who are our largest customers? Have our biggest customers changed positions over the years? Which data about our customers have issues? How should this data be cleaned?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once we have a good understanding of the data we’re working with and the general patterns and trends, we can begin to think of how we can create a model to predict which customers could potentially generate the most revenue for the company over the next 3 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And then finally, we’ll want to communicate these findings to management and the sales and marketing teams so they can start acting on our findings. We’ll want to create a dashboard for example so everyone can freely explore our findings and dive deeper into the data if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s interesting is that you could be a data scientist or a data professional that works across the entire workflow and usually in smaller organizations you’re going to have to do that. But in a large organization, you’ll find people specializing in a single aspect of this workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For instance, it’s generally a data-savvy management professional or a strategist that comes up with this question and identifies it as one of the most important things that a company should answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s a data engineer working with systems experts, database administrators, and cloud engineers to figure out how the data should be extracted from systems, transformed, combined, and stored.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s generally a business and data analyst that explores the data, identifies and rectifies its issues and they do this because they have a very good understanding of how the business works and they’re able to tell what’s good and representative data from what’s bad and inaccurate data. A data engineer could help here as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, and most people find this the more interesting part, it’s the machine learning model developers who decide between all the models they know of to figure out which one would get the job done best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And then, it’s the dashboard developers who prepare the reports and dashboards and tell stories to the management and sales and marketing team to convince them that this model is working well and according to its predictions this is who the company should focus on and if they do so, the company could earn 2 times or 3 times more revenue. These dashboard developers could be the business and data analysts as well since who better to tell stories than someone who understands the business deeply. There tends to be some overlap between these roles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And of course, let’s not forget that there will be a data science-savvy project manager overseeing the entire workflow and ensuring the work is getting done according to the set budgets and timelines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there’s a lot of different stuff you can be, how in the world do you decide between all of these roles? This takes me to the final thing I wanted to touch upon, and that is data science appeals to different types of people with different personalities as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005637.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005637.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s simplify your personality and let’s reduce it to two factors. One of those factors is how much you like working with people, the other is how much you like working with technology. There will be some of you, like me, that like working with both — a healthy amount of interactions with customers and management teams as well as interactions with systems and code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that our physical and digital worlds are so tightly integrated, you can’t really choose one and completely avoid the other but you may have a preference or a bias towards one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, wherever you may put yourself in this Venn diagram, there will be a role in data science for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you primarily enjoy working with technology, then you could consider roles like a machine learning engineer or a data engineer. These are really tech heavy roles that require you to, in the case of a machine learning engineer, spend time building models and algorithms and helping the company integrate it into their products or services. In the case of a data engineer, spend time connecting systems, making sense of the organization’s data, and making sure its data is flowing the right way through an organization so it’s available for analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you primarily enjoy working with people and overseeing them and interacting with them and organizing their work, you could consider a role like a data project manager or roles in data product sales which involves establishing a deep understanding of a company’s data product or service and then convincing potential customers to purchase it by telling them how it could solve their specific problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And if you enjoy working with both people and technology, you could consider roles in business and data analytics who are the middlemen between the more technical data resources within a company and the less technical business resources, they’re the translators and the storytellers who help decision makers make data-driven decisions. You can consider roles in business intelligence too and BI specialists don’t just figure out what kinds of dashboards or analytics business leaders need to do their jobs but they also make sure business intelligence tools are configured correctly and the data powering these dashboards is accurate, relevant, and up-to-date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an illustrative example and there may be some of you on the call who’ve got some experience or knowledge and completely disagree and believe that a project manager should sit in the middle or a data analyst should sit on the right or the lines between a data analyst and a BI specialist are really blurry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, different companies do things in different ways and because this is an emerging field the world really hasn’t reached a consensus on where to draw the lines between many of these roles. The key takeaway here is that you can do a lot more with data science skills than just be a guy or girl that builds machine learning models day in and day out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With data science skills you can carve your own path in the business world. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005643.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005643.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I stop for questions, I want to leave you with three things that I sincerely believe every aspiring data scientist should learn. This is regardless of your personality type because from experience it’s been incredibly beneficial to my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first is learning to tell stories. We often get lost in the rational and logical aspects of data science because, well, it’s got science in its name. But at the end of the day you want to use insights to convince someone to make a certain decision and what works is not raw facts and figures but emotional stories. This can be in the form of a speech or an interactive visualization or a web application, whatever it is, speak to people’s hearts using data, not their minds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second is learning to embrace mistakes. This is a field that’s growing insanely fast. There is so much I don’t know, there’s so much I need to learn, so naturally I make mistakes. I do the wrong things and I say the wrong things, but you need to be alright with not being perfect. It’s a lifelong learning journey and if you don’t let your mistakes get to you, the journey can be very rewarding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third is learning to empathize. By empathize I mean, putting yourself in the shoes of other people. You don’t necessarily need to be working in an office to do this, you can start by doing it with your friends at school. Whenever they’re facing a problem, try and understand how they feel and why they want that problem solved. If you can do this for your friends, you can do it for your colleagues and your customers and that’ll be very helpful in figuring out how you can use data science to actually enrich people’s lives in the working world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commence Q&amp;amp;A Session&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time today, I hope this was helpful. Feel free to connect with me on LinkedIn, just look for Stefan Jaro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need more information about data science, how you can get started in the field, how RI or RIC can help you, feel free to reach out to the RIC Career Guidance Unit. They’ll set you up for a career of success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again and have a great Friday evening.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>Questions to Reflect on When Considering a Job</title><link href="/questions-considering-job.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-27T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-07-27T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-07-27:/questions-considering-job.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Three questions to reflect on when you\'re considering a new job opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on LinkedIn: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:6957254865915928576/"&gt;Post Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three questions to reflect on when you\'re considering a new job opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will I be solving problems that interest me? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will I be in a supportive environment? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will I be earning enough to be comfortable? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your answer is \"No\" to any of the above, then keep working on yourself until the right opportunity arises because: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the problems don\'t even remotely interest you, you won\'t be able to sustain your enthusiasm after the initial new-job-honeymoon-period is over. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you\'re going to be in a non-supportive environment, you\'ll probably spend more time and effort on irrelevant problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you\'ll be struggling to pay your bills or support your family, you won\'t have the mind-space to focus on the problems you\'ve been assigned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>Well-being in an Economic Crisis: How Business Leaders Should Respond</title><link href="/well-being-economic-crisis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-14T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-07-14T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-07-14:/well-being-economic-crisis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you're a business leader in Sri Lanka right now, then the mental well-being of your employees should be at the top of your list of priorities.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;*Originally posted on LinkedIn: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:6949651126463934464/?updateEntityUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afs_updateV2%3A%28urn%3Ali%3Aactivity%3A6949651126463934464%2CFEED_DETAIL%2CEMPTY%2CDEFAULT%2Cfalse%29"&gt;Post Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're a business leader in Sri Lanka right now, then the mental well-being of your employees should be at the top of your list of priorities.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They're spending 8 hours or more creating a disproportionate amount of value for you, so the least you can do is make sure those 8 hours aren't adding to their growing list of personal problems.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't want them to turn into another brain drain statistic, give them every reason to stick by you through this economic crisis.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means not just having conversations about a resilient mindset but also creating company policies that serve as tangible proof of your commitment to their well-being.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may not be able to change the country's situation, but you can at least change how your business is responding to it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few ideas:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🏠 Allow people to work from home. If they do everything in front of a computer all day, they should not have to worry about getting fuel to get to work.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;💰 If you can't peg their salaries, at least provide some form of inflation relief whenever you can afford it. The gold standard would be a peg + inflation relief since inflation seems to be getting worse.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🫖 Conduct regular one-on-ones where you check up on each person, their workloads, how they're faring, and what kind of support they need. A short, friendly chat goes a really long way.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;😓 Cut the fat from everyone's workloads by de-prioritizing tasks that are non-essential. Encourage your employees to speak up when they feel like they're overwhelmed and are at the risk of burnout.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🧠 Offer professional therapy that's either paid for by the company or is at least subsidized. You may not be equipped to deal with some of the problems your employees now have in their personal lives and that's where a licensed therapist can help.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📚 Offer to pay for continuing education and MOOCs so your employees can continue to upskill themselves and stay competitive. Incentivize their pursuit of knowledge in these times.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🥳 Find any excuse to celebrate something. A new client. A good deliverable. A successful knowledge sharing session. Break the pattern of endless bad news with some joy and respite.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How else can leaders support their employees through this crisis?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>What Makes a World-Class Data Professional?</title><link href="/world-class-data-professional.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-06-10:/world-class-data-professional.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As we got more data projects, and more complex projects at that, we had to evolve from a rag-tag bunch of coders to an established data science and business intelligence unit.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was recently invited to speak at the launch event of the University of London M.Sc. in Data Science at the Royal Institute of Colombo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead of a generic speech on data science and it being the need of the hour at most companies, the Academic Coordinator encouraged me to touch on the more human-side of working in data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following is a raw transcript of my speech at the launch of the University of London’s M.Sc. in Data Science at the Royal Institute of Colombo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past four years, I’ve been in a very unique position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had surrounded myself with some of the brightest minds in problem-solving and Stax, the management consultancy I was at, was transitioning from primarily supporting our foreign consultants to becoming a center of excellence in technology and data analytics. This coincided really well with the growth in interest in data in Sri Lanka and among our American clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we got more data projects, and more complex projects at that, we had to evolve from a rag-tag bunch of coders to an established data science and business intelligence unit. Naturally with this came a lot of pressure to up-skill ourselves and we soon found out that there was a particular set of attributes required to be considered a world-class data professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say data professional and not data scientist because this is relevant for data analysts and data engineers as well. Most companies still haven’t drawn very clear boundaries between these three positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Often Forgotten Ingredient&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s get the obvious out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010540.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010540.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every data professional needs to have good statistical intuition. There’s no way around it. Statistics is the foundation of the entire field and at the very least you need to know your descriptive and inferential statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, every data professional needs to know how to use their tools and how to use it well. I’m talking about programming languages, development environments, visualization and dashboarding tools, and so on. This is a technical job so it’s a given that you need to be able to tap into the power of your computer and quite possibly a distributed network of computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on my experience of having worked with data professionals in Sri Lanka and amongst my clients offices, too many data professionals think that this is it. “This is all I need to succeed in business. I know my stats, I know my Python and now I’m ready for the big bucks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue with thinking that data science is the end and not a means to an end is that it can lead to scenarios where companies thump their chests and boast about the cutting edge models or technologies that they’ve implemented in the workplace. But when you look beneath the hood you realize that they’ve had little to no impact on their customers or operations, because they haven’t solved a business problem with financial implications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the missing ingredient here? What makes a world-class data professional?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is extremely simple but also very powerful: empathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010545.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010545.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we’re asking our sales people to have empathy, if we’re asking our customer service representatives to have empathy, if we’re asking our leaders to have empathy, then we should demand the same from our data professionals. They may not be on the front-lines unlike the other three, but aren’t these the people tasked with understanding, and making predictions about, our customers, markets, operations, and employees?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy is a powerful trait that influences every other desirable characteristic of a data professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Empathy and Problem Solving&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010552.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010552.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data professionals need to be great problem solvers because they’re in the &lt;em&gt;business of problem solving&lt;/em&gt; wherever they may work. What better way to solve a problem than by being empathetic? What better way to solve a problem than by putting yourself in the shoes of those you’re solving it for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a junior data analyst and somebody asked me to make a report or dig into the data to understand why something was happening, I thought to myself here’s the chance to show off everything I know. I’d make a big report with as many charts, graphs, statistics, and cuts of the data as I could generate and I’d present it to them proudly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I learned the hard way was that this was the worst possible thing you could do to a time-crunched executive. Give them way too many things to look at and make it very difficult for them to make a decision. What I realized was that I was lacking empathy by not respecting their time and their intentions. By wanting to show off what I knew, I wasn’t helping them achieve their objective which was to make a data-driven decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Empathy and Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010557.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010557.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy even influences the technology (or tech stack) chosen to solve a data problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning unlocks a lot of power and it has a wide number of applications. But with that being said, it’s not always the most optimal solution &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes it’s a very simple algorithm that can be easily explained, or sometimes it’s an Excel model that the client can play around with and validate as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, a solution should be based on a client’s level of comfort and preferences because this is the person (or the group of people) who will buy into the solution. The worst thing you can do is build something fancy and expensive that nobody uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World-class data professionals know this. They know that the utility of a solution is far more important than its composition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During our early days as a data science unit, we’d often deal with skeptical clients. People who hadn’t bought into the data-driven decision making movement yet. We discovered that the easiest way for us to convince them was to start with a simple and explainable solution that immediately delivered value and won their trust. We were then able to leverage that trust and familiarity to propose more complex and more sustainable solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Empathy and Communication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can’t be a data professional if you can’t effectively communicate and empathy is what makes world-class data professionals, world-class storytellers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They don’t parrot a list of facts, figures, findings, and trends because they know that logic and reason alone don’t influence decisions and actions. Emotions influence decisions and actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I really like to do with any big data finding is look for the supporting small data stories or anecdotes to back up an overarching trend. I like to look for stories about people and their experiences, stories that an audience can relate to, so that they personally resonate with the analysis and that makes it much easier to drive my points home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World-class data professionals also speak in the language of their audience. They don’t use terms like “gradient descent” or “resilient distributed datasets” if their audience is largely non-technical. Instead, they paint words with pictures and pictures with their words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Empathy and Resilience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010604.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010604.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any data job is a tough job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes our clients don’t know exactly what problem they want to solve. Sometimes you have a dataset that’s extremely messy and you need to have conversations with multiple stakeholders to make sense of it. Sometimes you don’t know how to get something done because you’ve never solved this kind of problem before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is, working in data requires a lot of grit and resilience. You’re frequently going to be lost and confused and you’re frequently going to be making mistakes. A world-class data professional understands that being uncomfortable is the way of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when you have empathy, it makes things easier. When you have empathy, you know why you’re solving a problem. You know who you’re solving it for and you know how their lives will be made easier by your solution. When you understand your purpose and the impact you can have, this big picture perspective will make it far easier for you to be resilient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The management theorist, Simon Sinek, says that if you ask a bricklayer without perspective what he’s doing he’ll tell you he’s building a wall, but if you ask a bricklayer with perspective what he’s doing, he’ll tell you he’s building a home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Closing Statements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of homes, this university was once my home for 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s really great that the University of London now has a Masters in Data Science because if it’s anything like my experience of studying Economics, it’ll require students to not just be able to learn complex concepts but to challenge themselves to apply it to a variety of different problems. It’ll require them to learn as much from their colleagues and classmates as they will from their lecturers. It’ll force them to think from multiple perspectives, including the examiner’s perspective, if they want to excel. And in doing so, it’ll build empathy so they can be better and more resilient problem solvers, technologists, and storytellers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I look forward to a new generation of world-class data scientists from RIC.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry><entry><title>48 Lessons in 48 Months (eBook)</title><link href="/48-lessons-in-48-months.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-13T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-05-13T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-05-13:/48-lessons-in-48-months.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of the term, here are the 48 lessons I\'ve learned from my leaders, colleagues, and clients over the 48 months I spent at Stax, a global strategy consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first term I ever learned in consulting was \"Key Learnings\". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its definition is self-explanatory. Its purpose, however, is powerful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never move on from anything --- a project, an analysis, a report, a conversation --- without spending some time reflecting on what you\'ve learned. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, knowledge, like interest, compounds over time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of the term, here are the 48 lessons I\'ve learned from my leaders, colleagues, and clients over the 48 months I spent at Stax, a global strategy consulting firm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1wO8hgJXfC9nni5M9hMiCMPMABUi2IGd3/view?usp=sharing"&gt;Download the Book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of it is common sense really, but it\'s funny how you tend to forget the little things in the heat of a tough moment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Self-Promoting"></category></entry></feed>