<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jaro Says - Technology</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2022-05-17T00:00:00+08:00</updated><subtitle>Reflections, Technology, Analytics, and Stories</subtitle><entry><title>Learning from the Terra Luna Fiasco</title><link href="/learning-from-terra-luna.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-17T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-05-17T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-05-17:/learning-from-terra-luna.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;More than anything, this fiasco has reminded me that when we stray from logic and embrace emotions during decision making, we can get very badly burned.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Where were you during the great Terra Crash of 2022? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="terra-crash-chart.png" src="/images/terra-crash-chart.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was just a bystander watching the catastrophe unfold on Twitter. The Crypto community went through every stage of grief.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This can't be happening! We demand our money back, no matter the cost! Is there anything we can do to stop this? I can't believe I've lost my life's savings. I have to move on from this.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than anything, this fiasco has reminded me that when we stray from logic and embrace emotions during decision making, we can get very badly burned. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this piece, I'll be outlining the 5 lessons I learned about investing in Crypto as I scoured through hundreds of Tweets during the crisis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't dive into how or why it happened since it's been widely documented and there's still some doubt behind there being an "attacker". You can check out &lt;a href="https://www.coindesk.com/layer2/2022/05/11/the-luna-and-ust-crash-explained-in-5-charts/"&gt;CoinDesk's Analysis on the crash&lt;/a&gt; for more information or watch &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LVanuXZedbs&amp;amp;feature=emb_title"&gt;CoffeeZilla's breakdown&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 1 - Don't invest more than you can afford to lose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common sense: don't invest your rent payments, your life's savings, or money you've borrowed from someone else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can earn more if you invest more, but &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;IT'S NOT WORTH IT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; if the downside risk means not just losing your money but also your livelihood, relationships, and peace of mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These screenshots below were taken from Twitter. I've removed the display names and usernames to protect each person\'s privacy.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-e1652808988485.png" src="/images/image-e1652808988485.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-1-e1652809007472.png" src="/images/image-1-e1652809007472.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-2-e1652809025684.png" src="/images/image-2-e1652809025684.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-3.png" src="/images/image-3.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 2 - If it's too good to be true, it probably is&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anchor Protocol promised returns of \~20% for depositing UST. This is incredibly high compared to traditional finance (or TradFi). Moreover, borrowing rates were much lower. Approximately 10% according to one &lt;a href="https://www.fool.com/the-ascent/cryptocurrency/articles/heres-why-im-passing-on-anchors-20-apy/"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this begs the question: how is this system sustainable? If they're not earning enough from borrowings to repay their depositors (and assuming they can't meet the shortfall from staked collateral alone), how are they guaranteeing their advertised returns? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still wrapping my head around a lot of Crypto technobabble, but according to what I've read this was not meant to be a long-term offering. It was a customer acquisition play and their debt obligations were met through a combination of using their reserves and relying on the speculative value of LUNA. They were propping Anchor up artificially. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a short-term "too good to be true" offering that unfortunately unravelled before it could evolve. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-4.png" src="/images/image-4.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ercwl/status/1524836855530893314"&gt;whole thread above&lt;/a&gt; is worth a read. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 3 - Don't put your faith in arrogant founders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven\'t been following Terra for long so I have no idea if Do Kwon (its founder) was arrogant from the get-go or whether he became arrogant over time as his projects did well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He became known for &lt;a href="https://markets.businessinsider.com/news/currencies/terra-usd-ust-luna-do-kwon-poor-critics-crypto-crash-2022-5"&gt;calling his critics "poor"&lt;/a&gt;. He said there'd be &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EncryptedPedro/status/1524531474237640706"&gt;entertainment in watching 95% of Crypto companies fail.&lt;/a&gt;He had earned his "FU Money" and was clearly letting people know. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that being cheeky and snarky are what people love on Twitter, but he seemed to have been blinded by his arrogance and overconfidence. He was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stablekwon/status/1464897977793728514"&gt;warned about a potential vulnerability&lt;/a&gt; but instead of addressing concerns, he challenged billionaires to disrupt his project using a method that would reward them handsomely if it worked. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That seems like a breach of fiduciary duty to me, regardless of whether or not it was the same method used to start the death spiral of UST and LUNA. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-5.png" src="/images/image-5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 4 - Invest based on logic and facts, not emotion and belief&lt;/strong&gt;s&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"We believe in &lt;em&gt;\$SOMECOIN&lt;/em&gt;" is not a reason to buy. "Stay strong" is not a reason to hold. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-6.png" src="/images/image-6.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to get swept up in the emotions of a community. Especially one that's as loud and boisterous as the Crypto community. But if the only reason you're investing is that several anonymous people on a Discord server told you that &lt;em&gt;\$SOMECOIN&lt;/em&gt; is the next biggest thing, you're basically lifting your legs as they place the rug under your feet. Or you're unwittingly taking part in their pump-and-dump scheme where you'll most likely lose out on your investment before you can dump. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DYOR or Do Your Own Research always. If there's not enough information online, be skeptical. If you don't understand their Cryptobabble, be skeptical. If the founders are anonymous or haven't disclosed their experience and credentials, be skeptical. If their community seems like a cult, be skeptical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it's too good to be true, remember Lesson 2. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image-8.png" src="/images/image-8.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lesson 5 - The Crypto community still has a lot to figure out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrencies and Blockchain are still emerging technologies, with (in my opinion) a lot of unanswered questions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are algorithmic stablecoins actually feasible? Are fiat-backed stablecoins truly resistant to similar attacks? How do we measure the fair market price of a coin? Is there a point to technical analysis if so much is based on "hype" and emotions? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of work that needs to be done and undoubtedly, a lot more risks the community will need to take. But until we're at a point where we've figured things out, remember that this is a largely unregulated space. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're on a boat, the seas are rough, and you don\'t have a life jacket. Make your decisions accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technology"></category></entry><entry><title>The Best of Budget Sinobuds: A Deeply Personal Purchase Journey and a Day One Review of the Haylou W1 TWS Earbuds</title><link href="/haylor-w1-day-one-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-09-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-09-18:/haylor-w1-day-one-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been meaning to get a good pair of wireless earbuds for work.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718004750.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718004750.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's this viral video on YouTube of an excited teenage girl receiving a brand new iPhone for Christmas. She squeals in delight when she takes it out of the bag, her eyes radiating a million thank yous. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her hurry to place her hands on a premium assembly of rare minerals and human ingenuity, she opens the box the wrong way and drops the phone on the ground. Cautioning voices behind the camera instantly turn into gasps of frustration. She picks it up, looks at the screen, and bursts into tears. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You watch this and you think, "God! Why can't people be a little more careful with electronics!? Especially brand new ones!? Why don't they understand the value of money? What's wrong with some people!? I know she's just a kid but come on, as a teenager, she's old enough to know better!" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I dropped the charging case of my Haylou W1 TWS Earbuds as I was popping it out of its packaging. Sure, it's no iPhone but it did cost money and it is brand new. Thankfully, it isn't damaged (visibly at least). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesson learned. Don't judge people in viral videos. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello!? Can You Hear Me!?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been meaning to get a good pair of wireless earbuds for work. Like most of you stuck in a pandemic-induced WFH loop, I'm on calls for several hours every single day. It's really frustrating when you're tight on time but you can't hear someone clearly and you need to, again, run through a near-ritualized troubleshooting process: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it my internet? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it their internet?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it my headset?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it their headset?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it my audio configuration?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it their audio configuration?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it Teams/Zoom?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I need to restart my computer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do they need to restart their computer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can't we just get on a regular phone call? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I certainly didn't want to be the source of auditory annoyance for anyone else, much less my clients, so I've been using a trusty wired headset with a microphone extension for the longest time. I got it for cheap (less than 10 dollars or 2000 Sri Lankan rupees) but it's been great, people have been able to hear me well, and I'm very rarely the source of an issue. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking the Dystopian Leash&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing about a wired headset though. After a year-and-a-half of working from home, it leaves you feeling like you're putting a leash on yourself each time you get on a call. There's only so far you can travel from your laptop before the jack pops out. And I've learned that I think and speak better when I'm on my feet and I'm pacing about. I've tried walking around with my laptop but after a while it feels like you're on a dystopian dog walk --- the robots are walking you! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some calls like webinars or company announcements where you need to only be listening and I've been wishing I could break away from the screen and wiggle my body around a bit so it doesn't gradually freeze into a permanent sedentary state. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all this in mind I had three primary requirements from a wireless headset: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It needs to be relatively cheap and available in Sri Lanka.&lt;/strong&gt; Like any decent Asian, I'm awfully sensitive to high prices, but like any decent techie, I also understand that you need to spend a bit if you want something good and will last long. This dichotomy was made worse by the fact that our import restrictions have reduced the flow of new electronics to a trickle and this trickle is now ridiculously marked up. With few good choices, this was going to be tough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It needs to have an acceptable microphone with good noise filtration.&lt;/strong&gt; I'm not ashamed to admit that I talk for a living but this means my livelihood depends on the clarity of my voice. I     tested out an old pair of wireless earbuds that I received as a gift a year ago but my ceiling fan made it sound like I was hanging off a helicopter. Noise reduction was a must!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It needs to have satisfactory battery life.&lt;/strong&gt; Last year I purchased a cheap single-ear Bluetooth headset. I wanted to feel like a busy corporate executive (in pyjamas instead of a fancy suit)     that's always on the go (in my home instead of a bustling office). Unfortunately, it had a terrible battery life and had a very bad habit of announcing "Battery Low, Please Recharge" over and over again in my ear during the worst possible moments. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll notice that high-quality audio isn't in the list above. I love music, but I'm not an audiophile and my current pair of earbuds gets the job done for me. Besides, this is meant for calls and I was ready to sacrifice output for input. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn't have to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718004928.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718004928.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earbuds? Sinobuds!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sri Lanka's good relationship with China has translated into almost every online electronic store carrying a wide range of Chinese goods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not complaining. Over the years Chinese electronics manufacturers have really upped their game. Their stuff is pure value for money now. I've been using a Redmi Note 9 Pro for the last 10 months and I haven't had a single thing to complain about. Now I'm not a flagship guy, but compared to the mid-range Samsung, Nokia, and HTC phones I've used, the Redmi has been nothing short of fast, snappy, and sleek. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured I'd choose among the many Chinese earbuds and when I started my search, one brand, in particular, stood out because they've flooded the market with a variety of models: Haylou. They're quite a new company but they've secured funding from Xiaomi who are the manufacturers of my phone, so that earned them a nice, big, green check-mark of approval in my book. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being relatively new to the market, they're certainly not obscure. They've got quite a decent following of product reviewers and quite a number of customer reviews too. When I couldn't decide between the Haylou GT3 Pro, the Haylou GT5, the Haylou Moripods and the Haylou W1, these guys came through for me. To the ones who've added chapters to their YouTube videos that allowed me to immediately skip ahead to the microphone test: thank you, I hope you are blessed with everything you desire in life. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CD32rrF7IXU?start=365" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the information I had, I rolled the dice on the Haylou W1 and bought it for roughly 7,800 Sri Lankan rupees (or 40 USD). I really wanted the blue version but every store I checked selling it for a reasonable price had only the white. I'm not disappointed though, the white still looks pretty neat and overall, I think the price is a steal given the microphone's quality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impressing with Impressive First Impressions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full disclaimer: I've been using the Haylou W1 Total Wireless Earbuds for only a day now, but like all narcissistic product reviewers I believe that to be sufficient enough time to share my detailed observations with you. In fact, I've come up with my own framework for reviewing these earbuds. It's called BATMAN or &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;attery, &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;udio, &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;ouch, &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;icrophone, &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;esthetic, and &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;oise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the &lt;strong&gt;microphone&lt;/strong&gt; since that's one of the primary reasons I bought this. I've been on calls the entire day and everyone's been able to hear me very clearly. Somebody even said that I sounded better through this microphone than the one on my wired headset. Huge win and that's probably down to the 4 microphones this bad boy has in its stems, 2 in each earbud. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part is the &lt;strong&gt;noise&lt;/strong&gt; cancellation. I decided to be a bit of a jerk and generate some noise in the background while speaking to a friend and they weren't able to tell I was being a jerk! This is fantastic! I can now freely dash pots and pans in the middle of frustrating meetings and totally get away with it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005037.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005037.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not a monster, I did listen to a bit of music and one podcast with it (&lt;strong&gt;audio&lt;/strong&gt; in other words). Now I can't comment on highs and lows, or bass and treble, or whether some hips are more truthful than others, but what I can tell you is that it's very decent for its price point. Imagine Dragons sounds good, Kanye sounds good, Doja Cat sounds good, and you can hear the tea-toned specks of saliva flying off British lips during the BBC's World Service (that's an exaggeration but they do sound good). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005053.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005053.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this while I've been draining its &lt;strong&gt;battery&lt;/strong&gt; but it's doing just fine. Some earbuds tend to stutter and lose connectivity when they're low on charge, but I haven't had that problem yet. The website promises 6 hours on a single charge and 20 hours overall with the case. I can only speak non-stop for 4 hours a day so I think I'm good. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;touch&lt;/strong&gt; controls are very simple so they're perfect for my simple mind. If you wanted me to summarize them I'd say: touch to stop, touch to start, touch touch to skip, and touch touch touch to call the nice Google lady on your phone. I was afraid it would be too sensitive and switch off every time I brushed my ear but it turns out I don't brush my ear as much as I thought I did. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718005103.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718005103.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the &lt;strong&gt;aesthetic.&lt;/strong&gt; There's definitely a little bit of AirPod Pro copycatting going on but there are hints of their own style as well, especially with the stem. They're light and they fit snugly so you can wear them comfortably for hours while blocking out some noise. I recommend wearing them while meditating so you can hear the therapeutic beats of your heart. I'm not crazy about the build of the charging case. The lid seems a little loose (although that could be from when I dropped it), it's shaped like an egg, and it's smooth and plasticky, but this is probably just me being pedantic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I'm impressed. I definitely believe it's worth 40 USD. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Before You Leave, A Message From Our Sponsors&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm kidding, Haylou didn't sponsor this article. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was curious about what Haylou meant. I figured it was something about audio in Chinese. Probably something meaningful. Perhaps renewing or augmenting our basic human auditory capabilities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, I was both right and wrong. Haylou is just how they pronounce "Hello" over there. But that "Hello" can spark a deep appreciation of the human voice...and for some reason, of the ocean through a conch shell. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not kidding, here's what's on their website: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand name is taken from the homonym of the English word "Hello". &amp;gt; We believe that we can resonate with the sea through conch and listen &amp;gt; to the voice of the ocean together, and we can also listen to the &amp;gt; voice of users through Haylou and share the beauty of the voice &amp;gt; together. Haylou is the messenger of sound and the medium through &amp;gt; which we resonate with our users. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever their copywriter was smoking that day, I want some.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technology"></category></entry><entry><title>Digital Mindfulness or the Act of Being Mindful of What You Consume Online</title><link href="/digital-mindfulness.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-16T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-02-16T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-02-16:/digital-mindfulness.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;20 pieces an hour across 6 hours is 120 pieces a day. Across a week that's 840. Across a month that's 3,650. And across a year that's 43,800.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many of us spend upwards of 6 hours online either for work or play. Let's assume that during these 6 hours we consume a minimum of 20 pieces of content an hour whether it's videos, photos, articles, statuses or comments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20 pieces an hour across 6 hours is 120 pieces a day. Across a week that's 840. Across a month that's 3,650. And across a year that's 43,800. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's just based on my conservative estimate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, that's 43,800 times your mind can be influenced in various ways. Just as a movie can make you feel the pain or happiness of its main characters, every piece of content makes you feel something. They either delight you, inform you, frighten you, bore you, or anger you. Every piece releases some chemical in your brain and when it all snowballs together --- 43,800 times --- it shapes how you think. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you want to lose weight, they tell you to be mindful of what you put in your body. They say, "great bodies are made in the kitchen, not at the gym". And when you follow their advice and eat healthy consistently, your body changes and reflects the goodness and richness of what you're feeding it. You become stronger and healthier. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very same applies to your mind. Every single thing you feed it, shapes it. If you feed it a stream of bite-sized, short-form content you will train your mind to pay attention and focus for only seconds or minutes at a time. If you feed it a stream of news that causes nothing but anger and fear, you will train your mind to see doubt and danger everywhere and with everyone. If you feed it a stream of content that causes nothing but amusement and joy, you will train your mind to be oblivious to the suffering of others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we see, is what we are. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have to accept that we cannot tear ourselves away from our screens. Not everyone can afford the luxury of selling their belongings and retreating into a forest to become a hermit. Our devices are now an extension of our being. They augment the way we entertain ourselves, build relationships and make a living. There are incredible advantages in their use. There's no running away from it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which leaves us with only one course of action --- extending the act of mindfulness to the digital realm. Being aware that what we do with our devices is affecting us in ways we may not know. Being conscious that too much of screen time, especially on applications engineered to instill addiction, can lead us down a spiral of anxiety and eventually, depression. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most of all, being selective with what we choose to put into our minds. Shying away from the ill-informed and superficial and gravitating towards the learned and enlightened. &lt;a href="https://ideas.ted.com/love-the-news-but-hate-clickbait-and-fluff-how-to-be-a-slower-and-more-thoughtful-news-consumer/"&gt;This article by Cal Newport on TED Ideas is a great place to start&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our thoughts shape our spaces and our spaces return the favor”
Steven Johnson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make every single one of those 43,800 pieces of content work in your favor. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2019/02/our-digital-lives-dont-need-to-make-us-unhappy-unhealthy-and-unwise"&gt;"Our Digital Lives Don't Need to Make Us Unhappy, Unhealthy, and Unwise" on the Harvard Business Review.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technology"></category></entry><entry><title>The Field Guide to Spotting Fake News in the Wild</title><link href="/field-guide-spotting-fake-news.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-08-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Stefan Jaro</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-08-10:/field-guide-spotting-fake-news.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;All you need is a simple blog/website, a Facebook page or Twitter account to distribute and promote your articles, and a bunch of pseudo-journalists blessed with a fake-news-writing ability.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fake news is a ridiculously profitable industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the margins are incredible! You don’t need a team of well-connected journalists spending too much time fact checking before publishing. You don’t need highly-paid editors ensuring compliance to basic morality and media ethics. And you certainly don’t need to bother with quality over quantity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All you need is a simple blog/website, a Facebook page or Twitter account to distribute and promote your articles, and a bunch of pseudo-journalists blessed with a fake-news-writing ability. An ability that is quite easy to develop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010245.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010245.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone was once a child with a vivid imagination, right? So if you’ve still got a little bit of that imagination in you and you’ve lied &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; a few times in your life, then you too can take an event that actually took place, exaggerate the details, sprinkle a few lies here and there, misquote the sources, add more “credible sources”, and finally top it off with a sensationalistic Can-You-Believe-This-Happened headline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeat this for a couple of dozen articles and soon you’ll be attracting thousands of clicks, and thousands of eyeballs on those ads littered across your website. Each click will be a &lt;em&gt;cha-ching&lt;/em&gt; in your bank account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conning Generations of Internet Users&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it sounds absolutely absurd and it should be very simple to see right through a piece of fake news for what it really is, it’s insane how many of us are so easily conned into believing something that just isn’t true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, does your mom or dad use an instant messaging app like WhatsApp? If so, go take a look (with permission of course) at what they’re sharing and what they’re receiving from your aunties and uncles. I bet you that somewhere in the cluster of messages there’ll be an old wives’ tale being passed off as a revolutionary medical breakthrough that doctors despise because it means patients don’t have to be treated by them anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we can forgive our older generation though, because many of them (especially in developing countries) may be new to the room-full-of-cobwebs that we call the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do we excuse the hundreds of thousands of digital natives of our generation and the generations after us who grew up well aware of the presence of misinformation online and yet are still fooled by blatant nonsense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What ever happened to the old saying, “&lt;em&gt;Don’t believe everything you read online&lt;/em&gt;”?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fake News = Unnecessary Outbursts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your older cousin trying to rub a baked potato on your face as a cure for your acne because a video on www.acnegoneinaday.zimbabwe told her to do so, should be the least of your worries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake news, created with an agenda, can spread like wildfire, drastically shifting perceptions, worsening tensions between communities, races, and religions, and possibly even resulting in outrage and violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just recently in India, &lt;a href="http://indianexpress.com/article/india/west-bengal-communal-violence-one-arrested-for-sharing-fake-image-and-inciting-passion-4742488/"&gt;a still image from a Hindi movie of a man forcibly pulling a woman’s saree&lt;/a&gt; made its rounds on social media after it was falsely described as a picture of a Muslim man harassing a Hindu woman. A &lt;a href="http://www.hindustantimes.com/kolkata/bjp-it-cell-secretary-arrested-in-asansol-for-posting-fake-video-on-social-media/story-GSLBmA1746fQlk5YupJrgI.html"&gt;video of unknown origin&lt;/a&gt; falsely described as depicting two Muslim police officers beating up a Hindu man went viral as well. An old image from 2002 of the riots in Gujarat was falsely described as a photograph taken during the &lt;a href="http://www.firstpost.com/india/watch-west-bengal-communal-riots-decoding-the-factors-behind-the-violence-spread-across-many-districts-3781759.html"&gt;recent riots in West Bengal&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://indianexpress.com/article/india/west-bengal-communal-violence-bjp-spokesperson-nupur-sharma-shares-2002-gujarat-riots-image-calls-for-protest-at-jantar-mantar-4742737/"&gt;used as a propaganda piece by politicians to call for more protests&lt;/a&gt;. Each piece of fake news intensified communal tension in the already unstable West Bengal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year a photo of Syrian children who died during a chemical attack was &lt;a href="https://www.morningnewsusa.com/thailand-child-organ-trafficking-photo-facts-to-know-23128278.html"&gt;falsely described by fake news websites&lt;/a&gt; as a photo of children who had had their organs harvested by Thai kidnappers and organ traffickers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the story about Donald Trump signing a $110 billion arms deal with Saudi Arabia on his recent visit to the Middle East? Even mainstream news outlets carried the story. &lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2017/05/20/us-saudi-arabia-seal-weapons-deal-worth-nearly-110-billion-as-trump-begins-visit.html"&gt;CNBC&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/donald-trump-arms-deal-saudi-arabia-110-billion-911-terrorism-international-law-war-crimes-a7747076.html"&gt;The Independent&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://thehill.com/homenews/administration/334368-trump-to-sign-110b-defense-deal-with-saudi-arabia"&gt;The Hill&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2017/05/saudi-arabia-sign-arms-deals-worth-110bn-170520141943494.html"&gt;Al Jazeera.&lt;/a&gt; Probably because Sean Spicer, the (former) White House Press Secretary, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/presssec/status/865937500610723841?lang=en"&gt;announced it&lt;/a&gt;. However, upon closer examination, &lt;a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/markaz/2017/06/05/the-110-billion-arms-deal-to-saudi-arabia-is-fake-news/"&gt;a researcher at Brookings Institute discovered that there is no deal&lt;/a&gt;; there are only letters of interest and intent. The $110 billion arms deal story that led to so much outrage is allegedly a piece of fake news!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010253.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010253.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably a more harder-to-detect example of fake news. It took a seasoned researcher with contacts in the arms industry to detect it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So do we, the average joes, stand a chance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps not when it comes to complex and specific matters such as international arms agreements but in many other cases, yes. Just like the best antivirus for your computer is your common sense (&lt;em&gt;don’t click on any of those suspicious links!)&lt;/em&gt;, the best tool to use when determining the validity of a story is your own brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, as netizens with the power to share to thousands who may go on to share to millions, you have a great responsibility to ensure that what you’re sharing is 100% accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s even 0.0001% short of 100%, you should think twice about clicking that share button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to turn foolish trust into educated skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summon Your Inner Robot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t let your emotions take advantage of you when you’re consuming a piece of content. Much of the news today is created to elicit shock, anger, frustration or sadness, sometimes just by the headline itself. It’s the oldest trick in the book to drive traffic to a website to earn more ad dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So once you’ve read, watched, or listened to something, don’t give in to your finger just twitching to forward it to someone else. Turn on the rational part of your brain and walk that piece of content through this list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) Does the web address (URL) seem very similar to the web address of an established news provider?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it bbc.co.uk or bbbc.co.uk? Is it dailymirror.lk or dailymiror.lk? Is it cnn.com or cnn.co?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010259.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010259.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_fake_news_websites"&gt;latter in any of the above cases&lt;/a&gt;, then your internal fake news detection device should be dinging. Especially if the design of the fake news website is very similar (in terms of the logo, colours, layout or font) to the website of the established news provider it’s trying to impersonate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Check the sources and then double-check the sources!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the content piece contain any sources or references? If not, be suspicious. If it states “anonymous sources have revealed…”, be suspicious anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the item-in-question has quoted someone in a particular position at a particular institution, use Google to check if that person exists, if that position exists and if that institution exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if all of the above exists, it won’t hurt to look for an official statement or press release by that person or institution. It is possible that their statements have been misquoted or taken out of context to make the news piece more sensational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) Have any mainstream media outlets covered the story yet?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capture the gist of the video or article in as few words as possible and Google it. See if any credible mainstream media outlets (either internationally or locally) have covered the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large number of mainstream outlets carrying the story is a good sign. Although be warned, the details of the story may be very different to what you’ve seen on non-mainstream media. So it’ll be wise to go beyond the headline to reading the article or watching the video before jumping to any conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) In the case of a questionable photograph, use Google’s reverse image search.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a news piece is centered around a photograph, then use Google’s reverse image search to see if the photo is really what the caption associated with it makes it seem to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either download the photo or copy the URL of the photo by right-clicking it and selecting “Copy image address”. Then head over to images.google.com, click the little camera icon which will enable reverse image search and upload the image or paste the URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010307.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010307.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re using Google Chrome, you can simply right-click on an image and select “Search Google for image.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010313.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010313.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the results show the same photograph being used in an unrelated context, then you have every reason to be suspicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Check with the veteran warriors against fake news — Snopes and Hoax-Slayer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snopes.com and hoax-slayer.com have been engaged in the battle against old wives’ tales, internet scams, and fake news since the rise of the internet. They use meticulous research to determine if a story is entirely true, entirely false or contains some truth to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to search through Snopes or Hoax-Slayer for a story you want to verify is by copying a line from the article (or summarizing the gist of the video), pasting it on the Google search bar, and adding “snopes” or “hoax-slayer” after it before hitting the search button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6) What’s the other content like?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it’s a website, take a look at some of the other content pieces. If it’s a YouTube channel, take a look at some of the other videos. If it’s a Twitter account, take a look at some of the other tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pasted image 20230718010319.png" src="/images/Pasted image 20230718010319.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any of the other content seems overly sensational, has misleading headlines, or are completely unsubstantiated, then let your doubts arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7) Who has written the article and what else has s/he written?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the by-line! It’s either right after the headline or at the bottom of the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google the name to see if that person actually exists. Most of the time you can also click on the person’s name to see a list of articles s/he has contributed to the website. If any of them seem fishy to you, by a rule of thumb, I would advise against believing anything s/he has to say without proper evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absence of a by-line doesn’t always mean the news item is fake. The BBC for instance doesn’t have a by-line on their online articles. However the BBC is a world renowned media organization with a long-standing history of a high degree of credibility. Something many non-mainstream media outlets don’t possess. So the absence of a by-line on the website of a non-mainstream outlet should raise your suspicions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8) Don’t be &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know what &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt; does? He reads only the headline and creates his own biased story in his head. He doesn’t know that most media outlets use sensational headlines to attract clicks so he doesn’t bother reading the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That guy&lt;/em&gt; also doesn’t check the date of the article. He’ll share an old story and act like it just happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That guy&lt;/em&gt; takes everything too seriously. He doesn’t know how to tell satirical articles from serious articles. A &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt; is probably a heckler at a stand-up comedy show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If after all of this, you’re &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; not sure if a story is true or false, then check with a friend. Ideally a friend who doesn’t wear a tinfoil hat and believe every conspiracy theory in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And remember, you should always check to see if a news item is fake regardless of who shared it with you, how educated they are, and what they do. It doesn’t matter if it’s your uncle who’s a nuclear scientist; even nuclear scientists can give in to their emotions and share without fact-checking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop the Avalanche&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This list is definitely not fool-proof. It’s possible that a piece of content can pass through every test and still end up being fake. But it does pay to squint your eyes, move your head to the side and be skeptical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to hold our media outlets to a higher standard, even the ones we consider mainstream. We need to demand evidence, credible sources, and the entire unbiased picture, while taking responsibility for reading the entire story, comprehending it, and not letting our personal biases or prejudices get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is our collective responsibility to prevent the spread of fake news and in turn prevent the outbursts that fake news has a tendency to generate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the brightest minds in &lt;a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/gadgets-and-tech/news/facebook-fake-news-feature-uk-election-2017-a7720506.html"&gt;social media&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2017/apr/25/google-launches-major-offensive-against-fake-news"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt; continue to tackle this problem with improved algorithms, new tools, and stricter regulations, they still have a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake news and its creators will always find a way to wriggle in, but we can stop giving them the pedestal that they do not deserve by thinking twice before we click “Share”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, it only takes one snowflake to start an avalanche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other References&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ifla.org/publications/node/11174"&gt;How to Spot Fake News&lt;/a&gt; (International Federation of Library Associations and Institutions, 2017)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Technology"></category></entry></feed>